<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned treatise in three parts, 1 The definition 2 The distribution of Divinity. 3 The happinesse of man;  as it was scholastically handled by John Stoughton D.D. in Immanuell Colledge Chappell in Cambridge, while he was fellow there: and now published according to the copy left under his own hand.</title>
            <author>Stoughton, John, d. 1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856923</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856923</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22565</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13022)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22565)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1293:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned treatise in three parts, 1 The definition 2 The distribution of Divinity. 3 The happinesse of man;  as it was scholastically handled by John Stoughton D.D. in Immanuell Colledge Chappell in Cambridge, while he was fellow there: and now published according to the copy left under his own hand.</title>
                  <author>Stoughton, John, d. 1639.</author>
                  <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ric. Hodgkinson for John Bellamy, Daniel Frere and Ralph Smith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: A.B., i.e. Anthony Burgess.</note>
                  <note>The words "1 The definition 2 The distribution" are enclosed in brackets on the t.p.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part 3 of: Stoughton, John.  XIII. Sermons (STC 23313).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22565:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22565:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LEARNED TREATISE: In three parts,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>The Definition of Divinity.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>The Diſtribution of Divinity.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>The Happineſſe of Man:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As it was Scholaſtically handled by JOHN STOUGHTON D.D. in Immanuell Colledge Chappell in Cambridge, while he was fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low there:</p>
            <p>And now publiſhed according to the Copy left under his own hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Ric. Hodgkinſon</hi> for <hi>John Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy, Daniel Frere</hi> and <hi>Ralph Smith.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22565:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22565:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His inſuing diſcourſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Definition</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution</hi> of <hi>Divinity,</hi> and the <hi>Happineſſe</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> was left perfected by the Author, under his own hand, as you have it here preſented to you.: The Author in the former Sermon laying down an exact Syſteme of <hi>Divinity</hi> and entring upon the explication of it, it might have been expected according to the method of Art, that he ſhould have begun with the Definition of it. But he did purpoſly omit it there, becauſe it was an Argument too Scholaſticall, for a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Auditory, but he having finiſhed this in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie in an exerciſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the trayning up of the ſons of the Prophets, I thought it fit not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale
<pb facs="tcp:22565:3"/>it, but to inſert it in this place, that ſo the treatiſe might be the more comple at: If it doe in ſome things exceed the capacity of the ordinary Reader, he muſt remember that the Argument it ſelf is more Scholaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call then popular, yet much of it may be uſefull to moſt, and all of it delightfull and profitable to the ingenious Scholar, to whom it will be the more profitable if he do peruſe the reſt of the Treatiſes: Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is a practicall Art, not only ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and ſo the end of it is operation: He is the beſt Schollar, and beſt underſtands what Divinity is, that hath learned to know and worſhip <hi>God</hi> ſo, that he may live well here and happily hereafter: If in this Treatiſe or thoſe other Sermons, to which this is annexed, things doe not fall out to thy mind, divide the blame betwixt the Printer and Tranſcriber, and rather lay it upon the publiſher then the Author: So I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, <hi>A. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22565:3"/>
            <head>THE DEFINITION OF DIVINITY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label>
                  <note place="margin">Praeface to the Auditors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſcope.</note> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F <hi>Plutarchs</hi> diſcourſe be reaſonable, that a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſhould be ſo far from being ſhy and ſhunning the converſe with great Men, that are in place and magiſtracy, that they ſhould take moſt pleaſure in taking paines to inſtruct them becauſe their lives being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary, their labor with them might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the benefit of the whole common weal: as a Phyſitian that hath any ſparke of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous honeſty will delight more in the cure of that eye which ſees for many: and if that be recorded of that of the Jewes in the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22565:4"/>hiſtory as an act of Barbarous inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, <hi>that they poyſoned the fountaines in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the Chriſtians,</hi> or mankind rather: then will I labor to forget the difficulty of this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiment, and rather think upon the publick utility of ſuch an exerciſe appointed for the training up of the <hi>Sons of the Prophets,</hi> the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>the eyes</hi> (as they call the Univerſities) that ſee for many, the healing of the waters (by caſting ſalt into them as the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> did) <hi>whoſe ſtreames make glad the citty of God,</hi> the Churches throughout the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the waters,</hi> ſayth the Preacher, thy ſeed in fruitfull ground <hi>in locis irriguis &amp; propterea benedictionis feraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> as <hi>Junius</hi> expounds it. Caſt it as I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, with a ſecure cheerfulnes in hope of a rich and copious benediction.</p>
               <p>He that makes an harpe would go more willingly about it, if he were aſſured, it were for one that would build the wals of <hi>Thebes</hi> with it as Amphion did: he that makes an helme if he knew it were to guide <hi>Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> his ſhip, in which he fought for the liberty of Greece, or <hi>Pompeyes</hi> in which he overcame the Pirats, or the famous Argo, in which the ancient Heroes fetch'd the golden fleece, and I think ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> the Artificer had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hew and ſquare that wood in which <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> laws were to be written, then of which a plough or ſome ſuch ruſticall inſtrument
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22565:4"/>ſhould be made: The accommodation is as eaſie for me, to incourage to this worke in hand, in this ſeminary of Religion and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: as it was for him to provoke Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, to apply themſelves to great perſons: for ſtudents in Divinity are like tables in which not the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>Solon,</hi> but of <hi>God</hi> are to be written, and thoſe that poliſh them with precepts, hew and ſquare them, fit for that imploiment: like Pompeyes ſhip in which God overcomes the enemy of mankinde the Divell, the moſt dangerous Pirat, who is therefore ſtiled in Scripture <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: like Themiſtocles, that fights for the liberty not of Greece, but of the Goſpell: like Argo that brings the golden fleece, the grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, who is the <hi>Lambe of God that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the ſinnes of the World,</hi> as <hi>John</hi> cals him: and they that furniſh them with inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, do as it were make an helme to guide them: they are like Amphion that build not the wals of Thebes but of the new Jeruſalem, and he that explains the <hi>Principles of Religion,</hi> the <hi>Analogy of Faith,</hi> tunes an harpe for them, by whoſe ſweet harmony the living ſtones come together into the building: And theſe places of learning if any, are thoſe waters of the preacher which are <hi>feraces benedictionis,</hi> like that good ground in the parable that yeelds increaſe a hundred fold, or like the land in Babylon, that with good huſbandry as you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22565:5"/>have it in <hi>Pliny</hi> gives a hundred fifty encreaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Artic. </seg>2</label> Now that the graine may hold ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with the ground, the ſeed with the ſoyle, and have ſome ſuch multiplying virtue as they ſay the virginian wheat hath, every corn of which ſends forth many ſtalks, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>every ſtalk in the multiplicity of ſides as it were in ſo many little granaries, ſtores up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcores of graine; I have made choice (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inſtitution and nature of this exerciſe) to handle the <hi>fundamentall points of Divinity,</hi> which though they may ſeem as they are few in number, yet are many in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, in ſight ſmall, but great in weight, like gold which being ſoild is contracted into a narrow room, but may be drawn into ſo large an extent, that one Angel may cover an whol acre of ground as you know the naturaliſts have obſerved: And becauſe it was the counſell of <hi>Polybius</hi> for hiſtory <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to frame a body of it, which is applyed by a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divine by better right to <hi>Divinity.</hi> I purpoſe to follow that adviſe and contrive a body of <hi>Divinity:</hi> wherein if you find me va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the form, yet you ſhall not for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: if weakeneſſe make me erre, yet ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornes ſhall not make me an heritick: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold it any ſhame after <hi>Auſtin</hi> to write <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractations</hi> profeſſing my name among thoſe, <hi>qui proficiendo ſcribu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; ſcribendo proficiunt,</hi> as he ſpeaks.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:22565:5"/>
               <p>I know it will be objected againſt this courſe that I ſhall not be able to make any great progreſſe in it, muchleſſe finiſh it, and therefore might more profitably propound ſome ſhorter project.</p>
               <p>But I anſwer firſt, though I ſhould but make an entrance, yet I ſhould meet with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matters of great importance &amp; uſe (as you ſhall perceive) which have not been explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the memory of the greateſt part of this Auditory.</p>
               <p>Second, I hope to ride ſome way becauſe I intend to point at onely all petty paſſages and to proſecute them alone, which I ſhall judge fundamentall and neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Third, that which ſhall remaine I meane God willing to fill up at other opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>One thing more I deſire you to remember, that as he ſayd by way of Apology for himſelf, of the harſh &amp; barbarous names of towns that are in the Catalogue of thoſe things that will not be written in a florid ſtile <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the Greek; elegantly: ſo may I ſay of ſome things in <hi>Divinity;</hi> that you may not look for ornament in my diſcourſe, but emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Verba noſtra non lenocinia eſſe volumus ſed media,</hi> to ſpeak with <hi>Salvian:</hi> The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of houſes are laid under ground, and madnes it were you know, to carve or paint them: and ſo it were to deck and trim the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22565:6"/>fundamentall points of <hi>Divinity:</hi> they <hi>would</hi> be ſo fine (as we ſay of ſome effoeminate gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants) that they would be the worſe for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> And thus without any more premiſed in commendation of this manner of proceeding, I begin with that which firſt offers it ſelfe in the conſideration of any Art, <hi>the Definition of Divinity:</hi> which I will propound two wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Divinity according the rules of Art.</note> Firſt according to the <hi>Method of Art;</hi> which as a ſtrait garment to the body keeps cloſe to the nature of the thing expreſſing it exactly, and cutting off all other things counting them but ſuperfluities.</p>
               <p>Second, according to the <hi>Method of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> which gives a little more ſcope; which inclines and bows truths, without injurious violence, to the condition and ſatisfaction of the Auditors, in regard of ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. The firſt I conceive thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Divinity is a Doctrine of mans Happineſſe.</hi> Or in equivalent termes, <hi>of living well and happily:</hi> wherein you have according to the law of <hi>definitions,</hi> two portions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>the generall,</hi> conteining the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, by which it agrees with other Arts and Sciences; it is as they are, a <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, <hi>the ſpeciall,</hi> conteining the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, by which it is divided and differenced from all other and conſtituted that which it is in its own peculiar <hi>eſſence,</hi> which two if they be rightly taken the definition muſt needs be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22565:6"/>accurate; and therfore that this may better appeare, I will indeavor to open them both ſeverally and diſtinctly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Artic. </seg>2</label> Firſt of the <hi>generall,</hi> that it is a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> by a Doctrine I underſtand a comprehenſion or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly of certaine catholicall precepts that are homogeneall one to another, and tend to one common ſcope as you know, for I do but borrow theſe from the ordinary notions without much ſcanning, becauſe that ſutes not with this exerciſe and argument, in which a Divine muſt preſuppoſe not proove thoſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall principles: and the matter is not great whether you call it a Doctrine, or a Diſcipline, or a Science, or Art, or Prudence, or Sapience: all which words may be put upon, in the ſame ſignification, though in diverſe reſpects, as I might eaſily ſhew, if I were not afrayd I ſhould be prevented by the time in more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial things: but in this indifferency &amp; choice of words I rather call it a Doctrine then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe it is in more common uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the beſt Divines then any other (which is the beſt rule to follow in this caſe) and ſounds moſt gravely and fitly in my eare.</p>
               <p>Second, Becauſe it prevents an ambiguity, which lyes hid in the other, for whereas an Art is properly, thoſe Catholicall precepts, and truths, which as I ſaid it comprehends, whether a man be habituated in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22565:7"/>of them or not, whether they be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in books, and delivered or not, as the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitians you know teach you to diſtinguiſh thoſe termes of Science, Art and Prudence and the like, ſignifying primarily habits of the underſtanding, have miſled many (and all the School-men) and made them miſconceive the nature of them as though they were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but intellectuall habits, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are conſidered as attained by us, but this reſpect is but accidentall to them and ſeperable, and no wayes eſſentiall.</p>
               <p>Third, I might adde that as thoſe Arts which they call Mathematicall, have their name from learning, becauſe by reaſon of their difficulty they are not often attained without learning from others, or becauſe it was one of the firſt and common things, which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient were wont to learne: ſo this name of <hi>Doctrine</hi> attributed to <hi>Divinity</hi> may inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate (as ſome have obſerved) the impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of attayning to this ſkill without a teacher <hi>(How can I underſtand without a teacher,</hi> ſayd the <hi>Eunuch</hi> in the Acts to <hi>Philip</hi>) and withall the excellency of the Doctor becauſe all that come to it muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, taught of God as the Scripture ſpeaks, we have <hi>one Doctor,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Cathedram habet in coelo qui corda docet,</hi> according to the Father: and ſo there will be a great Emphaſis in this word <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:</hi> And for theſe reaſons, though the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22565:7"/>matter be of ſmall conſequence, and though in the originall of it, it import but an extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall and adventitious relation of teaching, I rather prefer this, and call it a Doctrine: and this is the gneral part of the definition, though not a Genus in exact language and rigor of ſpeech, becauſe as I apprehend it, the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Art is not <hi>generis in ſpecies,</hi> but <hi>adjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti in ſubjecta,</hi> all the diſtinction of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken from the Objects as all agree, which in an Analogicall ſenſe are ſaid to make a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificall difference between habits: and as in Method we call the precepts generall or ſpeciall, though the diſtribution be not of that kind, but <hi>integri in membra</hi> as in Logick, and the ſame may be ſaid of others.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Artic. </seg>2</label> But it may be ſaid that this ſeemes not the full, and immediate <hi>Genus</hi> (for ſo we will call it) becauſe it expreſſes only that agreement which every Art hath with another, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as without doubt ſome have neerer affinity to ſome then to other, for example, <hi>Divinity</hi> to Ethicks then to Geometry, and ſo are tyed together in neerer references: In anſwer to this I ſay,</p>
               <p>Firſt, the diviſion of Arts is taken (as I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted even now) from the ſubjects by which the ſame thing in eſſence comes to be multiplyed and diverſified, ſo that the Generality of that word <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſeemes to be ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained and limited by the mention of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22565:8"/>proper object without any further curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
               <p>Second, It being not agreed what is the beſt and moſt accurate diſtributions of Arts, I judge it more convenient to reſt in that which is commonly received, and had rather that Generality too much ſhould be taxed as inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, then too much particularity ſhould breed obſcurity, eſpecially conſidering that this is a place not to examin, but to ſet a work thoſe grounds which <hi>Divinity</hi> muſt needs borrow from higher Arts.</p>
               <p>Third, to give ſome ſatisfaction I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of theſe three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt of the <hi>kinde of this Doctrine</hi> (the thing now in queſtion) out of the lawfull ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Arts.</p>
               <p>Second, of the <hi>condition,</hi> whether it be <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia</hi> or no.</p>
               <p>Third, of the end whether it be Practicall or ſpeculative; of all very briefely.</p>
               <p>For the kind I will mention but a double Series of Arts out of which you may fetch the <hi>primum genus</hi> of <hi>Divinity,</hi> the firſt is known to the moſt or many of you, where Arts are firſt divided into Generall and particular, then particular into Mathematicall and Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; Philoſophicall againe into Naturall and Morall; Morall into the root Theology, and the branches Ethicks; Oeconomicks and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks and the reſt; ſo that if you would frame
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22565:8"/>the next <hi>Genus</hi> of <hi>divinity</hi> you muſt call it a Particular Art the root of Morall doctrine &amp;c. I might produce many other of ancient and moderne authors if it were needfull or profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but I will onely ſuggeſt a ſecond, and that in a word: as many precepts about a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſubject collected make one Art, ſo many Arts make one <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, between every of which there is as lawfull ſequence and ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination as there is between the ſeverall parts of the ſame Art: ſo that all are truly one, though we divide them (and not amiſſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) for our commodity, as <hi>Suarez</hi> relates the opinion of <hi>Aegidius</hi> and <hi>Antonius Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula</hi> concerning <hi>Metaphiſicks:</hi> now the hint of this diviſion muſt be taken from the <hi>Objects</hi> as I noted before: Therefore if the object of Art in generall, be <hi>ens,</hi> in generall as is commonly ſaid (and for ought that I know truly) the ſpecies of Art will accompany the Species of <hi>ens,</hi> and goe hand in hand with them: Now <hi>ens</hi> is firſt divided into <hi>Increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> and <hi>Creatum</hi> (ſuppoſing this to be an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogicall diviſion according to the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived opinion, though there can be no gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall community between God and the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as the Schoolemen ſhew) and ſo <hi>ars</hi> is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>de ente increato,</hi> or <hi>de ente creato:</hi> Art <hi>de ente creato,</hi> is either of it in generall or in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: that in generall ſhall treat of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and affections of it and the ſpecies, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22565:9"/>ſo cut out that which the particulars ſhall make up, which borrow their ſubjects from it: for all being compriſed there where any affection or ſpecies ſwels to too great a bulk, it will ſend forth a colony as it were, and erect a particular Art: For example, <hi>Reaſon</hi> is a generall affection of <hi>ens creatum,</hi> which is ſo large that it deſerves particular conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo ſpeech, ſo quantity, whence Logick, Grammer, Mathematicks are riſen: ſo there is ſcarce any ſpecies of created nature, whence ſome particular Art is not budded: the laſt of which, man, more fruitfull then the reſt is branched into many: all which guide him in his operations towards his happineſſe and perfection, as the generall Art (wherein he is handled as well as the reſt) regulate him in his eſſence and conſtitution: and they conſider man either ſingle or in ſociety, concerning man ſingle, either in <hi>ordine ad Deum,</hi> which is <hi>Divinity,</hi> or in <hi>ordine ad hominem,</hi> which is <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks:</hi> and out of this you may collect more ſtrictly the proper <hi>genus</hi> of this Doctrine from the ſpeciall habitude to the neereſt object, which is the operations of man ſingle, or eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man as dirigible toward happines: and this may ſomething give light and limits to the generality of the word <hi>Doctrine</hi> which I uſed; But I will not inſiſt upon theſe Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicall and generall notions, which are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſought into by reaſon of the difficult ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22565:9"/>from particulars, but for the ſame reaſon, are very ſcientificall; and hee that ſhould travaile in them with diligence &amp; dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, ſhould do very good ſervice to all ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: &amp; ſo leaving the firſt inquiry concerning the kind of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> I come to the ſecond, concerning the <hi>quality,</hi> whether it be <hi>Scientia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Artic. </seg>3</label> I promiſe a diſtinction and anſwer it brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>Scientia</hi> is taken two wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for an <hi>Intellectuall habit</hi> apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an infallible truth, and this is according to the notion of the word moſt proper, and then the queſtion will be whether our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Theologicall truths be <hi>Scientia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, by a <hi>Metonymie of the Adjunct</hi> for the <hi>Subject,</hi> for the truths themſelves appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and this is moſt pertinent to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for you may remember I ſayd that was the beſt meaning, when we ſpeak of an Art or Science, and then the queſtion is whether the precepts in Theology be ſuch as are the Subject of ſuch an habit, as we call a Science. <hi>viz.</hi> of infallible truth, Catholicall and Scientificall.</p>
               <p>According to this latter ſenſe I anſwer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatively to the queſtion, that they are, and therefore it may juſtly challenge the name of a Science: the precepts in this being as in other, deſinitions, diſtributions and conſectaries that explaine proprieties, all which make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall and Catholicall axioms: and if it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22565:10"/>be objected that many things in Divinity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendupon contingent fact, as the <hi>fall of our firſt parents,</hi> and the <hi>Incarnation of our Saviour,</hi> with the reſt of his performances, for the Redemption of man kinde, of which there cannot be a perpetuall and unvariable rule: I ſay,</p>
               <p>Firſt, theſe inſtances are but few (not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more I think then I have named) and therefore can bring no prejudice to an whol Art.</p>
               <p>Second, <hi>Divinity</hi> makes not a bare hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call narration of the contingent fact; but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that explaines a conſtant affection with which it's proper Subject, man, in order to his happines, is inveſted upon thoſe occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Third, I diſtinguiſh the exiſtence and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, or rather the condition of the things, and the connexion in the Rule, the former is contingent and mutable, yet the latter may be notwithſtanding immutable and conſtant: But theſe things ſhall appeare more plainly afterward. If the queſtion be put in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſence, whether our knowledge of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall truths be properly Science: I ſay,</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is not much materiall what it be.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the conſideration of an Art is extrinſecall to the nature of it, as I conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before of an Art in generall.</p>
               <p>Second, if that were regarded according to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22565:10"/>the diverſe habitudes, to diverſe apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the form would be diverſe habits, yea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in one <hi>Scientia</hi> (as without queſtion the knowledge that <hi>God</hi> hath of <hi>Divinity</hi> is <hi>Scientia,</hi> in another opinion which appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends them not without doubting <hi>cum formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine oppoſiti,</hi> as the Schoole ſpeaks, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Faith</hi> that aſſents to them only, becauſe commended to him by <hi>divine</hi> authority; and ſo the ſame habit of Theology, would be all of theſe, and by conſequence none of them, which were abſurd to ſay: but to come up cloſer to the point I ſay,</p>
               <p>Second, that it may be more fully anſwered by this diſtinction of <hi>Scientia: Scientia</hi> may be taken three wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the <hi>knowledge</hi> of a Catholicall axiom, or an immediate propoſition as other Logicians call it, whatſover the condition of that knowledge be: and according to this acception the reſolution of this queſtion, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows from the former affirmative, becauſe there I determined that the precepts in this <hi>Doctrine</hi> are ſuch.</p>
               <p>Second, for the certaine knowledge of any axiom, whatſoever the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of it be: which is the moſt common ſignification of <hi>ſcire</hi> in common phraſe of ſpeech: and thus alſo the reſolution of the queſtion is affirmative, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the certainty of faith by which we aſſent to divine truths upon a divine teſtimony is as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22565:11"/>great as of any demonſtrative ſyllogyſme: and for this reaſon, ſaith <hi>Gregory de Valentia</hi> the nobility of this <hi>Doctrine</hi> deſerves the name of a <hi>Science,</hi> amd cannot well be ſtiled by any other.</p>
               <p>Third, for the evident knowledge of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion by a convincing reaſon, or demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and in this ſenſe it ſeems to be uſed by <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> and after him the Schoolmen, and according to this ſtrict acception the queſtion is more doubtfull: for this including that which was moſt reſtreined in both the former, that the object muſt be a Catholicall axiom as the firſt required, and that the aſſent muſt be certain, as the ſecond exacted, ſuperads three qualifications.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the Object muſt be a <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, that the aſſent muſt be evident.</p>
               <p>Third, that the motive muſt be a eonvin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Reaſon or demonſtration, as it were neceſſitating the underſtanding to aſſent: The firſt and laſt addition I paſſe over, as imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, becauſe few precepts of any Art are ſuch Concluſions, for neither definitions nor diſtributions (which make the greater part) are ſo demonſtrated being moſt prime, and immediate, and therefore cannot be proved by any that are <hi>priora</hi> or <hi>magis immediata &amp; perſe,</hi> then they are. Only it is ſaid that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions may be ſo demonſtrated of their proper
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22565:11"/>ſubjects which may well be called in queſtion by the ſame reaſon that I alleadged for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Second, few Arts have ſuch precepts except onely the Mathematicks as is obſerved, when it is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are grown almoſt into a Proverbe.</p>
               <p>Third, if they were neceſſary, Divinity is in the like condition with the reſt for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Art, though not for other acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: We will therefore enquire of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond condition, and propound the queſtion a new; whether our knowledge of Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall truths be evident or not.</p>
               <p>To anſwer it then with as much circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of judgement, and yet with as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle circumſtance of words as may be.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I lay this foundation, that <hi>Evidence</hi> is a metaphoricall ſpeech, from the eye to the underſtanding, and a relative thing impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a faire proportion of the object, to the faculty in both; ſo that there is a concurrence of three things to it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the aptitude of the object to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned.</p>
               <p>Second, the ability of the faculty to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne.</p>
               <p>Third, the diſpoſition of the <hi>medium</hi> fit for conveyance, which is diſtinct in the viſion, but included in the two former, in the action of the underſtanding.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:22565:12"/>
               <p>Second, I diſtinguiſh the three principall termes of the queſtion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the knowledge of which muſt be conſidered according to his different conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either in <hi>natura integra</hi> or <hi>corrupta,</hi> for many things he did know then ſcientifically, which now he doth ſo much as opinio native<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and againe as corrupted, he is either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſed in it, or elevated by the infuſion of grace.</p>
               <p>Second, the precepts of <hi>Divinity</hi> are in a double difference, ſome are <hi>aeternijuris,</hi> ſome are <hi>liberae voluntatis,</hi> that I may ſpeak ſo for diſtinction ſake: for inſtance, in the ſtate of innocency the promiſe of another life, to which <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have been exalted upon obſervance of the covenant, was <hi>liberae volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, as the moſt agree,</hi> and the precept of that I call ſo, though it alſo be indeed <hi>aeternae veritatis,</hi> as all rules of an Art ſhould.</p>
               <p>Third, Evidence is either in regard of the ſimple termes, the things themſelves, which by reaſon of more or leſſe abſtraction or ſuch like circumſtances, may be evident or obſcure, more or leſſe.</p>
               <p>Or ſecond, in regard of the connexion and cohaeſion of them one with another:</p>
               <p>And now thirdly, I reſolve the queſtion in theſe Aſſertions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, all <hi>Theologicall precepts areevident in themſelves though not to us,</hi> as <hi>Thomas Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:22565:12"/>of propoſitions that are <hi>per ſe nota ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſe</hi> though not <hi>quoad nos,</hi> of which this he gives as one <hi>Deus eſt:</hi> the reaſon is becauſe the termes are eſſentiall one to another as they muſt be in all Catholick axioms.</p>
               <p>Second, <hi>Man in his integrity had proper Science of all thoſe precepts,</hi> which I called <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris aeterni:</hi> though of the other, as a better ſtate in another life, he had not without a double helpe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>ex parte objecti,</hi> which was Divine Revelation to convey it.</p>
               <p>Second, <hi>ex parte facultatis,</hi> which was an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of grace ſtrengthening, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it; the reaſon of the firſt part of this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, that man had Science of thoſe which were <hi>juris aeterni</hi> is, becauſe they were evident of themſelves, and there was no impediment of his part, his faculty being proportionable to them: of the ſecond, that the other he could not <hi>ſcire</hi> of himſelf, becauſe they depended on the free liberall grace of <hi>God,</hi> which he could not penetrate, till it pleaſed him to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his good pleaſure by Revelation, and withall were ſupernaturall to him, and above his Spheare: the reaſon of the third part that thoſe helps ſuppoſed, he could, is becauſe then nothing was deficient, either in object or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, as I ſaid of the firſt three Aſſertions: <hi>Man faln,</hi> can know neither the one kinde nor other, ſcientifically and ſavingly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22565:13"/>Revelation of the object and elevation of the faculty, and then he may evidently: ſo that his knowledge may in truth and proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be called Science, for the reaſons hitherto intimated: I confeſſe I ſeeme in this to ſtrive againſt the ſtreame of the Schoolemen, who ſeem to make evidence of the nature of Faith, out of the Apoſtle, who ſaith <hi>faith is of things that are not ſeen,</hi> and make faith and ſcience oppoſite habits; but they alſo may admit a good interpretation: for I think they meane of the condition of ſome things, not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of the termes in the precepts, or of man conſidered with naturall reaſon only, to which I grant they are not evident: But if there be any doubt of this laſt (to which I have without any neceſſity condiſcended) I think the former anſwers may ſuffice: And ſo I will paſſe from this, adding but this one obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that when an <hi>Art</hi> or <hi>Doctrine</hi> is called <hi>Scientia,</hi> there is a Synecdoche in the word, for properly the knowledge of one ſcientifical axiom is a ſcience, and in that ſenſe, neither Divinity (as <hi>Durand</hi> and <hi>Ariminenſis</hi> well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute) are one Science, but ſo many conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (ſo they call them) as there are ſo many ſciences, yet by this Synechdoche as I ſayd the collection of many are called one, and are ſo <hi>unitate ordinis,</hi> which ſufficeth ſayth <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of Valentia to the unity of a Science.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Artic. </seg>4</label> And now I come to the third inquiſition
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22565:13"/>of the end, whether this doctrine be <hi>Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> or <hi>Practicall:</hi> where I premiſe a few neceſſary obſervations for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of it, and then reſolve it in a word.</p>
               <p>Firſt obſerve <hi>Speculative</hi> and <hi>Practicall</hi> are not ſpecificall differences of Arts and eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but accidentall only, as <hi>Valentia</hi> rightly judges more probable, though I like not his reaſon, becauſe ſayth he, they are taken from the objects as things, for Arts as I ſaid are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifically diſtinguiſhed by their objects in that large ſenſe of ſpecificall before mentioned, but becauſe they are taken from the habitudes, which Art, have to us, who uſe to aime at Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, or operation in the purchaſe of them and end in thoſe.</p>
               <p>Second, every Praxis doth not conſtitute and denominate a Practicall Art, but you muſt note a threefold latitude in the uſe of this word.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in the largeſt extent of the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it comprehends theſe three things under it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for all theſe are opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the firſt of the underſtanding, the ſecond of the will, the third of all the faculties.</p>
               <p>Second, in the narroweſt it is oppoſed on one ſide to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> on the other to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and then imports nothing but the ſecond, the <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitus actus voluntatis,</hi> as <hi>Scotus</hi> ſpeakes, or an immanent act perfected within it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Third, in the middle way it is oppoſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22565:14"/>to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but includes the two latter: now in both theſe latter acceptions, it is taken when we ſpeak of a practicall diſcipline, but more principally and more particularly in this queſtion, in the firſt of them the middle of the three:</p>
               <p>Third, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and character of a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall Science is not the end that any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar man makes to himſelfe, for that is fallible, for in both kinds of practicall, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they may propound to themſelves Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Gentleman may ſtudy Architecture for delight in the contemplation, and do ſtudy both Divinity and Morality whoſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe if it be not bare Speculation I know not, but the iſſue we ſee is not practiſe; therefore the judgement of this muſt be from the nature of the object, and the end of the art it ſelf: Theſe obſervations being thus diſpatched, I anſwer in a word affirmatively that Divinity is a <hi>Practicall Doctrine,</hi> and conclude this truth in this one Reaſon: That Art is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall whoſe Subject is <hi>res operabilis à nobis,</hi> in the language of the Schoole, and whoſe proper end is operation, for theſe make it practicall, and it is ſayth <hi>Durand</hi> very well, practicall, <hi>radicaliter à ſubjecto formaliter à fine,</hi> but Divinity is ſuch as ſhall appeare in the explication of the latter part of the <hi>Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> immediately ſucceeding; therefore <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity</hi> is <hi>Practicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22565:14"/>
               <p>Second, things may be objected againſt the Aſſumption of this Syllogiſme.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that <hi>God</hi> is the object of <hi>Divinity,</hi> who is not <hi>res operabilis à nobis,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt condition of a Practical Art is not found in this: I defer the full anſwer of this till I come to a particular deciſion of that queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ſhall be the next time, for the preſent I ſay <hi>God</hi> is not the ſubject of <hi>Divinity</hi> nor principally conſidered in it according to his nature for he that doth ſo ſayth <hi>Durand, ſumit formam Philoſophi,</hi> but in Relation to our works as they are terminated in him <hi>objectivè,</hi> and in ſome ſenſe that is true, which the ſame Author affirmes, not <hi>qua Deus,</hi> as the <hi>Thomiſts</hi> would have it, but <hi>qua ſalvator,</hi> not <hi>qua cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendus,</hi> ſay I, but <hi>qua colendus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, it is objected that the laſt end of Divinity <hi>is the viſion of God,</hi> which is ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and therefore the ſecond condition of a Practicall Art agrees not to Divinity, to which I anſwer.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the laſt end of Divinity is eternall happineſſe, but not the whol end, and in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happines that viſion is ſomething, but not all, for without doubt there ſhall be many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther operations, as prayſing of <hi>God</hi> &amp;c. To w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> that is rather ſubordinate then otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Second, the next end makes an Art Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call not the remote, but that viſion is as <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand</hi> diſputes: yet that is produced by an
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22565:15"/>habit of glory, which is of another kinde, then our habit of Divinity; but theſe things ſhall appeare better in that which follows: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſtill hold that concluſion that it is Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall: and that Scripture gives good teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to this truth, <hi>Evidenter apparet conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranti omni Scripturam a principio uſque ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quia ſemper pro una ſcripturae columna in qua agitur de his quae ſunt pure ſpeculabilia à nobis ſunt pluſquam quingenta folia in quibus agitur de pure practicis,</hi> as <hi>Durand</hi> writes: I will alleage ſome few places to make this good in part. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 15. <hi>The end of the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is charity.</hi> Out of which and ſuch like places <hi>Alexander Hales</hi> made it a third, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Speculative nor Practicall; but Affective, which opinion is true though not in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to practick, for that affection is in order to action, that that is the laſt: more plainly. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.17. <hi>All the ſcripture is profitable for doctrine for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to every good work: John</hi> 13.17. <hi>If you know theſe things, bleſſed are yee if ye doe them,</hi> ſayth our Saviour. <hi>James</hi> 1.22. <hi>But be ye doers of the word and not hearers onely deceiving your ſelves.</hi> I ſhall not need to heap up more: for <hi>Scotus</hi> and many of the beſt Schoolemen concurre in this opinion, and all our modern and orthodoxe Divines with one conſent agree in it: and therefore I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22565:15"/>this in the words of <hi>Bernard, Is recte legit Scripturas divinas,</hi> and ſo <hi>Theologiam, qui verba vertit in opera:</hi> Bleſſed are they that heare the word of <hi>God</hi> and keep it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Artic. </seg>5</label> The laſt time I propounded the firſt <hi>defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Theology</hi> conteyning ſo much, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived neceſſary for the accurateneſſe thereof: which was this that <hi>Theology is a Doctrine of mans happineſſe:</hi> and then I diſpatched the former and generall part of it, that it was a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> explayning foure things for the clearing of it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, how it was a doctrine and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I called it ſo, rather then by any other name.</p>
               <p>Second, what kind of doctrine in particular that ſeeming large and generall.</p>
               <p>Third, what manner of doctrine for the condition and quality whether <hi>ſcientia</hi> or not.</p>
               <p>Fourth, what was the end of it whether Speculation or Praxis.</p>
               <p>It remaines now that I proceed to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and particular part of that definition that this doctrine is of <hi>Mans happineſſe,</hi> that this ſame thing may be expreſſed in other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipollent terms I touched before, and mean not to trouble my ſelf, or you with unneceſſary ſcruples in that kind: whether you liſt to ſpeak as I have done, or like beter to call it, <hi>a doctrine of living well;</hi> with <hi>Ramus,</hi> or <hi>a Doctrine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22565:16"/>guiding man to his happynes;</hi> or ſuch like, the ſenſe being the ſame, the terms are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: but thus much I wiſh to be obſerved in the words.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that I call it happines rather then <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> becauſe this latter word in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acception there of implies and preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes a ſtate of evill and miſery from which man is to be ſaved, which is not generall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for our purpoſe, being but one parcell of that divinity doctrine as it is uſually and rightly handled of all, and as you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by that ſhort declination of the parts, which I ſhall make the next time.</p>
               <p>Second, I rather mention happynes in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall then eternall happines, as the moſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſſe, or underſtand it; for the ſame reaſon: becauſe though that be the higheſt and laſt and principall, to which all other things in Divinity are in their kinde ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, yet it is not all: for both <hi>Adam</hi> in the <hi>ſtate of integrity</hi> had actuall felicity, and ſhould ſtill have had ſo long as he continued in inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity &amp; ſo have the <hi>children of God in the ſtate of Regeneration,</hi> though they be tranſlated into the kingdome of heaven and glorified, though this be of a lower ranck and order then that other: ſo that Eternall happineſſe is too narrow for the generall end of this Art: except perhaps it be widened two wayes.</p>
               <p>Either firſt, by extending the ſignification
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22565:16"/>of the word eternall happineſſe (which is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily taken for that eſtate which abides with the children of <hi>God</hi> in the kingdom of heaven; becauſe that is to indure without alteration and change to all eternity) ſo that it may take that happineſſe of this life along with it, both together making but one context of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happines.</p>
               <p>Or ſecondly by changing the whole phraſe, delivering the ſenſe in theſe or the like terms that it is a Doctrine teaching to live well here, that we may live happily hereafter and that to all perpetuity, which will come to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: thus much you may obſerve for the word</p>
               <p>Second, under the word <hi>Happines,</hi> I compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend both the <hi>end</hi> it ſelf, to which that word is in a manner appropriated, and all thoſe <hi>means</hi> that lead unto it which are either, thoſe graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acts of God ſuch as are <hi>Redemption, Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Juſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Sanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> &amp; the reſt, or thoſe <hi>pious acts of man,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are neceſſary for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining thereof, eſpecially thoſe that direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and immediately have <hi>God</hi> for their object, being his proper worſhip and ſervice: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe actions have a Relation of efficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to that happines, under which notion we conceive of meanes ordinarily, and perhaps not amiſſe in this caſe, if we ſpeak of happines as it ſignifies that future eſtate of glory; or whether rather thoſe actions are parts of it, or happines it ſelf; which reſpect ſeemes to agree
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22565:17"/>better to it, as it is taken generally for the whol end of man, and makes the adaequate ſubject of this Art: becauſe as you know the Phyloſopher defines felicity to conſiſt in the operation according to virtue: And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this explication of the word, you may eaſily diſcerne that thoſe opinions would not ſtand in oppoſition one to the other, one of which ſaith that mans operations are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Doctrine: as <hi>Durand</hi> doth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing it in theſe words <hi>actus meritorius,</hi> (ſayth he in their Popiſh language) is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Divinity, and better <hi>actus humanus ordinabilis in beatitudinem:</hi> as <hi>Arminius</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in his private diſputations makes, <hi>actio homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis quam Deo praeſtare tenetur,</hi> and in word <hi>Religio,</hi> which is the ſame with the former, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it omits the reference that thoſe actions have to the end, happines, which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſame author addes expreſly in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of Theology: But the other makes Happines the ſubject of this doctrine: which hath no repugnancy to the former as I ſaid but includes it as ſubordinate: And thus I judged it to ſute better then the other: for theſe two reaſons,</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe <hi>actus Religionis,</hi> is not large enough for the whole latitude of Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call precepts for there be ſome, as I noted of the Acts of <hi>God</hi> which are neceſſary to make man happy: it being as impoſſible in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22565:17"/>courſe, that man ſhould bee redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to his perfection, his happines, without the culture of <hi>Gods grace,</hi> as it is that other infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior creatures ſhould be reduced to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, their laſt end; without intervention of mans care: there being the like proportion in the dependance of other creatures upon man, to be managed by him, that there is of man upon <hi>God,</hi> to be managed by him, and ſomething more:</p>
               <p>Second, the <hi>acts of Religion,</hi> may be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to happines by a more direct attribution then happines can be reduced to them: and therefore ſeeing both are conteined, and it is not needfull to expreſſe both, I made choice as neere as I could of the fitteſt: And ſo much alſo of the ſignification of theſe words.</p>
               <p>Third, therefore to diſpatch the explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this latter part of this definition, and ſhew how theſe words of <hi>mans happines,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the ſpecialities of divinity: they may ſuſtaine a threefold relation.</p>
               <p>Firſt, of the <hi>ſubject,</hi> becauſe this doctrine is converſant about the nature and affections and parts of happines.</p>
               <p>Second, of the <hi>form,</hi> becauſe Arts being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by their objects the form is alway included in them.</p>
               <p>Third, of the end, which indeed is prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily either of the artificer, or rather of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22565:18"/>and ſo ſecondarily may be conſidered as of the Art it ſelfe: the firſt therefore of the ſubject is the moſt principall and eſſentiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation as you ſee, and requires a little further illuſtration.</p>
               <p>That is the ſubject of a Science or Art ſaith <hi>Gregory de Valentia,</hi> which is the ſubject of thoſe concluſions (as he cals them) or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts that are principally intended in that Science: and diſtinguiſhes nicely between this <hi>ſubjectum &amp; objectum,</hi> which he makes the precepts themſelves where you may note <hi>ſcientia,</hi> to be taken for the habit of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: <hi>Durand</hi> alſo diſtinguiſhes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>ſubjectum in quo,</hi> which he makes the underſtanding to be of all Arts, and <hi>ſubjectum de quo,</hi> of which the preſent queſtion is, and that ſaith he muſt have theſe three condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it muſt be <hi>aliquid incomplexum ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet terminus &amp; non propoſitio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, it muſt be <hi>primo &amp; principaliter conſideratum in ſcientia,</hi> and all things there muſt have <hi>attributionem ad ipſum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Third, it muſt be ſuch <hi>de quo aliqua praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari poſſint denominativè:</hi> that third of theſe is obſcure by reaſon of a Scholaſticall terme, but included in the former, for any thing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall: and the two former agree with that I brought out of <hi>Valentia:</hi> ſo that not to hold you longer in this, I conclude that in a word
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22565:18"/>to be the ſubject of a Science, that is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Scientificall precepts therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined: now I aſſume, But mans happines ſo taken as I have explained it, including all the meanes unto it and the parts of it, is the ſubject of the precepts of divinity which are principally intended in it, as might appeare by a particular enumeration now, and ſhall better afterward: for except the definition it ſelfe of Theology, wherein it is a part of the praedicate it or ſome part or affection of it is the ſubject in all the reſt: there being many precepts of this Art, becauſe there be many particulars of this ſubject, as I ſhewed the laſt time that Arts are multiplied becauſe their ſubjects are multiplied: and the unity of a Science likewiſe depends upon the unity of of the ſubject: I conclude therefore that <hi>mans happineſſe is the Subject of Divinity:</hi> man is as it were the <hi>materiale</hi> and happines the <hi>formalis ratio ſubjecti:</hi> And thus much of this firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of Theology that it is <hi>a Doctrine of mans happines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There may be diverſe things objected both againſt this latter part, which I have paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more lightly and leſſe diſtinctly then I purpoſed for ſome reaſons, and againſt the whole: but I ſhall meet with them more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently in another place, and that by and by, and therefore will not meddle with them here, the rather alſo becauſe I have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22565:19"/>deteined you too long already in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance.</p>
               <p>Only give me leave to illuſtrate this defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the Scripture, for though the word of <hi>God</hi> aime not at the laying down of artificiall and notionall truths; but beats al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt altogether upon fundamentall in a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of divine wiſedome and prudence: yet even thoſe muſt have the ground and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantialls, from thence, though Art may put a form and modification upon them: therefore it will not be amiſſe to give ſome light to this definition out of it: The places are infinite, which I might alleage, but I will confine my ſelfe to afew, and that of two ſorts.</p>
               <p>The firſt point at it, in generall as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>John</hi> 6.68. <hi>Peter</hi> cals the doctrine of our Saviour, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for when our Saviour upon occaſion of the going back of many of his diſciples from him asked his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>will ye alſo go away,</hi> this is <hi>Peters</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; <hi>whether ſhall we go? thou haſt the words of eternall life: Luc.</hi> 1.77. It is ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for in <hi>Zacharies</hi> ſong this is ſaid to be the ſcope, and imploiment of <hi>John</hi> the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of <hi>Chriſt, to prepare the wayes of the Lord to give knowledge of Salvation to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the forgivenes of their ſins: Acts</hi> 13.26. <hi>Paul</hi> termes the preaching of the Goſpell by himſelf, and the reſt of the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: as that evill ſpirit in the maid, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.17.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22565:19"/>to the ſame effect in a Scripture meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor cals it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>the way of Salvation.</hi> I will content my ſelfe with theſe that I have already mentioned though many more offer themſelves and perhaps more preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort of places ſeeme more fully to comprehend the definition, of which it ſhall ſuffice to have produced but three, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3. the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth it in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a Doctrine of Religion or godlines, or according to godlines,</hi> which by ſome of our Divines is uſed in ſo many words to this purpoſe; and therefore I need not ſtand to explain it: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I obſerve that this defines it by the means to happines rather then the end happineſſe it ſelf, as you may remember I ſaid ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines did: the ſecond place is more plaine and full. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, where you may have both expreſly mentioned: the third and laſt place, is rather more accurate for, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. the Scriptures, and ſo the rule of Divinity conteined in them are thus circumſcribed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: I ſhould inlarge theſe with explication and accomodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them to my preſent ſcope, but they are perſpicuous of themſelves; and I have been too tedious in this matter: I will therefore ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22565:20"/>this onely in all together, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture inſtead of happines uſeth rather to name <hi>eternall life and Salvation,</hi> the latter becauſe it is directed all to man faln, who muſt be raiſed from miſery; ſo that his happineſſe is properly Salvation: the former, becauſe the moſt noble member of our happines is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, and therefore by a familiar Synech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doche names that for all and inſiſts in that: and both in a diſpenſation of heavenly wiſdome, becauſe they carry moſt majeſty and divine authority with them, and are moſt powerfull &amp; efficacious to work upon the heart of man: And ſo I leave this firſt definition, and paſſe to the ſecond.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Now the ſecond, as you may remember I ſaid in the beginning, is to bow the ſame truth a little to the common apprehenſion taking liberty to diſpenſe with the ſtrictnes and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Art, by Prudence, and that I think may be fitly conceived in theſe or the like words; <hi>Divinity is a Doctrine revealed by God in his word which teaches man how to know and worſhip God, ſo that he may live well here and happily hereafter:</hi> I intend not to ſpend any time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thoſe parcels in this definition, wherein it agrees with the former: and for circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall differences, I will paſſe them over likewiſe; becauſe I ſuppoſe there will not ariſe any difficulty, which may not tolerably be ſatisfied out of that which hath been ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:22565:20"/>
               <p>There be two additions onely of moment, which muſt be expended.</p>
               <p>Firſt, concerning the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, concerning the <hi>knowledge of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt, I ſhall cleare in the opening of theſe three propoſitions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that divine Revelation is not the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malis Ratio</hi> of the ſubject of Theology.</p>
               <p>Second, that mention of the Scripture is not to be inſerted into the definition of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, when we go about to lay downe the nature of it accurately.</p>
               <p>Third, that for ſome circumſtances of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence it may be convenient to do it: the truth of which three I ſhall ſhew in a word.</p>
               <p>For the firſt: <hi>Valentia</hi> diſtinguiſhing of <hi>formalis ratio quae &amp; ſub qua,</hi> makes <hi>divine Revelation</hi> the formall reſpect of the ſubject of Theology acccording to the latter, and the Thomiſts generally make <hi>ens divinum Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile:</hi> and make good the unity of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by that, though it treat of many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent things as <hi>God</hi> and the creatures &amp;c. Yet it is one becauſe all are conſidered in one for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall reſpect as they are revealed, which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: and he goes ſo far that in anſwer to an argument of <hi>Aureolus,</hi> to the contrary, that if that were true, if <hi>God</hi> ſhould reveale Mathematicks and Metaphyſicks to one man they would be but one Science becauſe there
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22565:21"/>would be the ſame <hi>ratio formalis ſub qua, viz.</hi> divine Revelation he thinks it no abſurdity to grant ſo much.</p>
               <p>But, I take it, this cannot be: for if Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were the <hi>formalis,</hi> by which any thing were brought into the compaſſe of Divinity; then,</p>
               <p>Firſt, nothing ſhould be handled there, but <hi>quatenus Revelatum,</hi> and ſo Divinity ſhould have no proper ſubject of it own.</p>
               <p>And ſecond, every thing <hi>quatenus Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> ſhould be handled there, upon which muſt needs follow this inconvenience that the truths of all Arts ſhould belong to Divinity, becauſe many of them are revealed in the Scripture (as for example, naturall, morall, Politicall, Hiſtoricall, Architectonicall, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicall, and almoſt of all kinds) at leaſt all of them may be revealed, if <hi>God</hi> pleaſed, as well as Theologicall are.</p>
               <p>And ſecond it would follow, that Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy ſhould not be diſtinguiſhed from other Arts by any eſſentiall difference; but only by this extrinſecall reſpect, of being revealed which may as I ſaid be a common affection of all truths: 'tis true indeed that <hi>de facto,</hi> all truths neceſſary to Salvation are Revealed and <hi>de jure</hi> they had need to be revealed, and if that opinion aimed at no more I think it ſhould offend not againſt the verity of the thing ſo much as the propriety of the language
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22565:21"/>but they ſeeme to ſay more, and in that ſenſe I reject it.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond, that mention of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not to be made in the definition of Divinity, when we go about to lay down the nature of it accurately I ſhew it thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe it is but an extrinſecall rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as hath been ſaid, and therefore as it were abſurd to ſay of Logick, that it is an Art of Reaſon delivered in <hi>Ariſtotles Organon,</hi> or in <hi>Ramus,</hi> and it were inconvenient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine any Art, that it was ſuch an one attained to by naturall reaſon and humane induſtry, (which have the ſame habitude, to the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of humanity that Revelation hath to the Doctrine of Divinty) ſo in a like (I ſay not an equall) proportion, it would be at leaſt unneceſſary to interpoſe this in the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Theology that it is revealed by <hi>God</hi> in his word:</p>
               <p>Second, becauſe it is not of ſo generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration as to be placed in the title and fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpiece of the Art, as may if you do but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,</p>
               <p>Firſt, the <hi>finis cui,</hi> or the object of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is either onely, or eſpecially <hi>man faln,</hi> in which eſtate it is abſolutely neceſſary that he ſhould have the word of <hi>God,</hi> to bee his guide toward his true happines.</p>
               <p>And ſecond, if you remember the efficient cauſe of the Scripture which beſide the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22565:22"/>the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> is inſtrumentall, <hi>holy men inſpired by God</hi> the pen-men of the holy Ghoſt which were alway extraordinary miniſters of the Church having ſuch immediate aſſiſtance of the Spirit: now both theſe the fall of man and extraordinary officers of the Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the nature and uſe of the Scriptures cannot well be unfolded, are of later conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and follow afterward in the body of this Art: and therefore the treating of the Scripture cannot be exalted ſo high as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition without an obſcure anticipation of exact order.</p>
               <p>For the third, that this notwithſtanding, it may be convenient to define it, ſo for ſome circumſtances of prudence, it will be no hard matter to demonſtrate.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe it conteines all thing neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Salvation, and therefore is coextended with the object of Divinity; and in this ſenſe alſo the Scripture may be called a Rule or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, becauſe though it be not every way ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequate, as that uſes to be (conteining many things in it which are not properly Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, as I noted before) yet it hath all thoſe things in it: but it is more aptly reſembled to a Rule or Canon, as it reſpects faith and things to be beleeved, with which it is every way reciprocated, for every thing revealed in the Scripture is to be beleeved, and every truth to be beleeved is revealed in Scripture.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:22565:22"/>
               <p>Second, becauſe all men now are in the ſtate of corruption of the fall, ſo that it is abſolutely neceſſary as the caſe ſtands for all men: and ſo it is well commended to all in in the very entrance as a principle and ground of all that followes, and is placed at the top as a candle upon a candleſticke to give light better to all the roome: And thus much of the firſt addition in this latter definition, <hi>that Divinity is a Doctrine revealed by God in his Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond follows, which is, that this <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine teaches man to know God;</hi> concerning which, I ſhall deliver my minde what I think in ſo many propoſitions likewiſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that <hi>God</hi> is not the ſubject of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Second, that he is not (according to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) at all to be handled in divinity.</p>
               <p>Third, that there is juſt reaſon why he may and ſhould according to the method of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               <p>The firſt may appeare by the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment negatively concluded, by which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that man, as he is to be guided to his end or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (which in a reaſonable nature is called happines) is the true ſubject about which all the precepts in this Art are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant: but I paſſe over that.</p>
               <p>Second, it may appeare by this reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe divinity as hath been proved, is a practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22565:23"/>Art not a Speculative: now a Practical Art is that whoſe end is operation and that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate not <hi>mediatè,</hi> as <hi>Valentia</hi> well obſerves, for the remote and mediate end of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templative Science, may be operation; and a Practicall Art hath alway ſuch an object, as is <hi>res operabilis à nobis:</hi> but if <hi>God</hi> be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, neither of theſe can agree to it, as it is more then manifeſt: therefore <hi>God</hi> is not the Subject.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, that <hi>God</hi> is not at all to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in Divinity, though perhaps it be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the former and might be proved by the ſame reaſons; if he be neither the ſubject nor part of the ſubject, yet becauſe it will ſeem more ſtrange to ſome. I will rather prove it diſtinctly, and ſeverally.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe Divinity, as we for the moſt part generally conceive of it, is a particular Art one of the loweſt and laſt: but <hi>God</hi> muſt be needs handled in the firſt, or very neer the firſt: for if <hi>ars</hi> be ranked according to <hi>ens, God</hi> who is the firſt being, may juſtly challenge the firſt Art at leaſt, next to that of Art in generall if there be any ſuch in the whole <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</p>
               <p>Second, becauſe if there were any reaſon why <hi>God</hi> ſhould be handled in this Art, it would be this, becauſe he is the object of the operations of man which are here regulated namely (in which regard I deny not, but he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22565:23"/>may be called a remote object of it) but this is not ſufficient, becauſe by the ſame reaſon the nature of man ſhould be handled here alſo, he being the object of ſome acts, as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of charity and the reſt: which to ſay would be held abſurd:</p>
               <p>Third, becauſe ſuppoſing that to be, true that it is an Art Regulating mans actions and directing him to his happines, which I think is out of queſtion, I cannot ſee how things of ſo different nature can be homogeneall to the ſame ſcope, and beſide the unity of a Science will not beare it, as <hi>Keckerman</hi> ſayth well, even in this reſpect, becauſe it ſhould be both pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall and Speculative, which are indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>computible though ſome Schoolemen have attempted ſuch a reconciliation: It may be objected,</p>
               <p>Firſt, that it can be handled in no other Art: But I have prevented this objection when I reaſoned that it muſt be in the firſt art, before we deſcend to the treatiſe of <hi>ens crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:</hi> and <hi>Bradwardine</hi> confirms me in this, ſaying that <hi>Deus eſt</hi> that truth is the firſt of all, upon which all other verities have depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</p>
               <p>Second, the very name <hi>Theologia</hi> argues <hi>God</hi> the ſubject of it: I anſwer.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I granted before that he is the remote object namely of mans operations performed to him, and that may ſalve the Etymologie.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:22565:24"/>
               <p>Second, the name ſuppoſed, the reaſon may be drawn otherwiſe then from the ſubject, as from the author and efficient <hi>God,</hi> or from the end becauſe it is to bring us to <hi>God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Third, which <hi>Durands</hi> Arts (or habits as he ſpeakes) are many times denominated not a <hi>formaliratione ſubjecti,</hi> but a <hi>digniori,</hi> &amp; ſo it might well come to paſſe that Divinity, which is <hi>Scientia ſalutis humanae,</hi> might be denominated from God: where I obſerve that he fals upon the ſame definition that I have given.</p>
               <p>Fourth, the impoſition of the name uſually follows the common opinion (which was ſo, I confeſſe) rather then the accurate truth of things, which perhaps would rather call this art <hi>Anthropologia,</hi> or ſome like name then <hi>Theologia:</hi> laſtly the conſent of all may bee objected as a prejudice againſt this opinion: But I anſwer.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is no ſtrange thing for many to erre in ſuch a matter of notion, artificiall rather then ſubſtantiall truth, and yet many give good hints of that which I have ſaid.</p>
               <p>Second, the error hath been not ſo much pofitive in defending, as negative in not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending or expending this truth, not ſo much of judgement maintaining, as practiſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, which alſo they had good reaſon for, which I muſt ſhew in the laſt propoſition,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, therefore I ſay that the Doctrine
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22565:24"/>of <hi>God</hi> is not unfitly handled in Divinity.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the nature of God and our actions tending to happineſſe are of ſo neere affinity, for the former affords a firm ground to build the latter upon, ſo that the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that is neceſſary to this which indeed ſhould be ſuppoſed out of an higher Art as I have often intimated; but ſeeing God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates the knowledge of the one, to men of the common ſort, it would not be expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to diſtract them between two arts; but it is much better to compriſe them in the ſame, by a diſpenſation of Prudence condeſcending to their capacity.</p>
               <p>Second, becauſe they are conjoyned in Scripture in which the knowledge of both is conveyed unto us joyntly, therefore Divines finding them there together thought it not meet to ſeperate them in their treatiſes.</p>
               <p>Third, this is a ſingular priviledge and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the Schoole of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that in it all Chriſtians beſides the way to their own feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, in which they are properly directed, do withall learne the knowledge of God in all his excellencyes, which muſt needs adde much grace and majeſty to the former: and thus much of this third propoſition, and of both the definitions of Divinity in generall, me thinks too much, and yet when I looke to the particulars too little, too jejunely &amp; nakedly.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:22565:25"/>
               <p>The uſes may be,</p>
               <p>Firſt, for inſtruction to teach us that this Art concernes all, every one muſt be of this trade, for it is of Mans felicity.</p>
               <p>Second for exhortation.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to <hi>thankfulneſſe,</hi> ſecond to <hi>diligence,</hi> from the <hi>Certainty, Nobility and Neceſſity</hi> of this Doctrine.</p>
               <p>I will not trouble you with repetition of any thing that hath been formerly delivered, only becauſe that which follows hath the riſe and ground out of that which is gone before, Let me call to your mind the definitions of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, which I have hitherto propounded and in ſome homely manner expounded, and that in generall only: the firſt was a <hi>Doctrine of mans Happineſſe, or of living well and happily,</hi> which I thought ſufficient for accurateneſſe: the ſecond was this, that <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is a doctrine revealed by God in his word, which teacheth man to know and worſhip God ſo that he may live well here, and happily hereafter.</hi> Which perhaps as I ſaid may give more popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſatisfaction though according to the rules of Art, if it were examined, there may be ſome ſuperfluityes in it to be cut off as I ſhewed: and thus having only preſented theſe a freſh to your conſideration, that you may the more clearly underſtand the ſucceeding diſcourſe, I begin with that where I left, then to draw ſome practicall obſervations out of that which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22565:25"/>hath been taught, before I proceed any further: and they ſhall be but two.</p>
               <p>Firſt for <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> we may learn from hence that this Art or Doctrine belongs not to ſome few, onely, but concernes every man to know and practice.</p>
               <p>Second for <hi>Exhortation,</hi> and that twofold.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to <hi>thankefulnes,</hi> that God hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us like trees by the rivers of waters, and taking ſuch care to guide us in the way of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
               <p>Second, to <hi>diligence,</hi> in the uſe of thoſe meanes and golden oportunityes, which God hath afforded us, toward the gaining of our happines in this ſeminary of Religion and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which we cannot let ſlip unleſſe we will ſhamefully betray our owne ſoules.</p>
               <p>The firſt appeares out of the definition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a doctrine of mans happines: where you ſee both the <hi>materiall ſubject man,</hi> and the <hi>formall happines</hi> intimate unto us, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the conſideration of the generality of this Art, that the uſe thereof extends it ſelfe indifferently unto all men: indeed if there be any that have drunk ſo deep of <hi>Circes</hi> cup, that are ſo bewitched with the Sirens ſongs ſo beſotted with the charmes of pleaſure, that they have put off the ſhape and name of men, and are turned into beaſts, or if any that beare the name and ſhape of men are ſo degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their nature that they are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22565:26"/>to confeſſe themſelves altogether voyde of humanity; they may perhaps conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to that hypotheſis though not reaſonably, reject this Art as nothing appertayning to them: but if they be men <hi>homo ſum, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas nihil à me alie num puto,</hi> as you know he ſaid, if they be men, this is the doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning man to guide and regulate him, of which therefore they may not only claime the uſe, but alſo challenge propriety in it: for it is a <hi>Doctrine of mans happineſſe:</hi> man may be conceived as the materiall object of it, and ſo that implyes the generality of it reaching to every man: Againe if there be any Art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning man, which perhaps concerns not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man in particular, and ſo the former il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration be thought inſufficient; yet that which is of mans Happineſſe, the generall end of all, muſt needs belong to all: except there be any that have ſo far defaced the image of God in their Soules, that they have blotted out alſo even thoſe common principles which nature hath left engraven and imprinted not only in men, that are endued with the higheſt perfection of reaſon, but alſo in all creatures (at leaſt in a kind of Analogy) that have but the loweſt degree of being; all which have a naturall <hi>impetus</hi> or <hi>appetitus</hi> to their perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which in the reaſonable nature is called properly <hi>Happines:</hi> and though men be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in their deſires and inclinations toward
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22565:26"/>particular good, ſome affecting one thing ſomeanother according to the variety of their diſpoſitions, yet all agree in this generall, all hunt after happineſſe: Though <hi>bonum</hi> be not defined according to the proper eſſence accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, <hi>quod omnia appetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> yet with the empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall article. I think it may be not abſurdly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed as the Philoſopher hath done it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: that good is that which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one deſires, every one deſires to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: and though all they miſſe their marke when they thinke to finde it here below, <hi>bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam vitam quaerunt in regione mortis,</hi> as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſpeaks, yet in groſſe they aime at this: and therefore this Art, as this end, is generall and concerns every man: And thus it appeares that this obſervation is reduced out of the former definition, which I therefore mention leaſt any here ſhould think the ſtudy of this <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enum opus,</hi> a matter that pertains little to him, and therefore behave himſelfe as it is ſaid of <hi>Gallio</hi> in the Acts, <hi>as if he cared not for theſe things:</hi> whoſoever thou art if thou haſt but the nature of a man, if thou haſt but any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o happineſſe, <hi>hoc ad te pertinet,</hi> the ſtudy of Divinity belongs unto thee: the wiſdome of ſwaying ſcepters and managing Kingdomes and Common wealthes, which the Philoſopher ſtiles the Architectonicall art, may preſcribe to every man a particular im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment and vocation, according to their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22565:27"/>naturall abilities in ſubordination to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick utility, but every one muſt take this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him, this is the generall calling of all men, which they muſt walke in directing all their actions to this end: this is one diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from other Arts: The great Turk himſelfe they ſay, you know though born to beare rule and inherit the Empire, yet beſide is trayned up to ſome trade of life, which he exerciſeth perhaps in his Royall pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace and chaire of eſtate: I am ſure the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Princes and Potentates muſt be ſkild in this trade or elſe all their glory will be not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſplendida ſervitus</hi> as he ſaid, but alſo <hi>ſplendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da miſeria:</hi> the Rabbins had ſuch a conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that all their Doctors together with the profeſſion of Divinity ſhould joyne the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of ſome handicraft: what the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of that was I know not, but I ſee a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the contrary, that every craftſman with the profeſſion of his craft, ſhould joyne the practiſe of Divinity; Some are imployed in <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> ſome in <hi>Merchandiſe,</hi> ſome in <hi>Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture,</hi> or otherwiſe, but from the higheſt Stateſman to the loweſt craftſman, all ſhould be divines; all ſhould be imployed in this: Not ſo that every one ſhould be, or labor to be a teacher of others, as we commonly take the name of a Divine, otherwiſe then that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall obligation to the private duties of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as admonition and the like, that is not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22565:27"/>my meaning: but that he ſhould be able at leaſt to teach himſelfe and guide his owne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the laſt end of all his happineſſe: And thus far I ſay it ſtands every one in hand to be a Scholar in this Schoole, leaſt any ſhould be miſ-led with that vulgar opinion which rejects all knowledge and ſtudy in this kind, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Divines: But wherefore then hath God tempred the ſtile of his word, and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to the capacity of all ſorts of men; <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ipſe dicendi ſacrae Sripturae quo contexit?</hi> ſayth <hi>Auſtin, quamvis paucis penetrabils omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tamen acceſſibilis:</hi> that I may a little alter his words, <hi>Nam quae aperta continet ea quaſi amicus familiaris ſine fuco ad cor loquitur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doctorum ac doctorum: eaverò quae in myſteriis occultat, neceloquio ipſo ſuperbo erigit, quo non audeat accedere mens tardiuſcula &amp; ineru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita quaſi pauper ad divitem ſed invitat omnes humili ſermone quod non ſolum manifeſta ſed etiam ſecreta exerceat veritate &amp;c.</hi> And wherefore hath God erected his oracles every where in his Church, and his Schools and the chaire of <hi>Moſes</hi> in every Congregation, to have them taught and expounded: whereas other Sciences are profeſſed and practiſed in ſome places only of the Commonwealth: but that they belong to all, &amp; muſt be part of the care of every man? but I need not urge this, neither did I purpoſe any more then to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it when I firſt thought upon it: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22565:28"/>in this place and among you, who both by the generall appellation that is given to U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſityes, that are called the <hi>Schooles of the Prophets,</hi> and by particular ſituation of this, compaſſed with hils as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the <hi>vally of viſion,</hi> and by proper dedication of this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whoſe gates will ſcarce admit of any, but ſuch as are at the leaſt welwillers to Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but as <hi>Plato's</hi> Auditory exacted Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometry <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo this ſeemes to examine as it were and poſe every one it receives in their purpoſe for Divinity <hi>Sacrae Theologiae ſtudioſis poſuit:</hi> All which do put you in mind that howſoever others may ſtand affected to this ſtudy, yet it behoves you to be in a ſingular meaſure addicted thereunto, and deſire to be in the number of thoſe that not only in the Apoſtles words, <hi>let the word of God dwell in them richly and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully,</hi> but alſo labor for it, and therefore as it were dwell continually in the ſtudy of it: and true it is of theſe places that <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaks, I think of his mother at leaſt a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mother, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or to that purpoſe for I do not well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his direct words: they are mothers in <hi>Iſrael</hi> to nurſe and give ſuck; that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the ſincere milke of the Word</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> cals it to us that we may prove <hi>Nathaneels true Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites in whom there is no guile:</hi> ſo doth ſhe deſerve that title of <hi>Alma mater,</hi> which you
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22565:28"/>ſee written in her Arms: and we may well beare that deviſe which <hi>Domitian</hi> uſed where his word was this <hi>optimae matris:</hi> as you have it in <hi>Tacitus:</hi> And thus much of the firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation that the uſe of this Doctrine extends it ſelfe generally to all men, and to us in a more particular manner: wherein becauſe I have been longer then I purpoſed, I will paſſe over the reſt, though more material, the more briefly.</p>
               <p>The ſecond follows for <hi>Exhortation,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt to <hi>thankefulneſſe</hi> upon a double ground.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that <hi>God hath ſet us in ſo honorable a ſtation,</hi> a calling ſo worthy as you ſee that of a Divine muſt needs be, whoſe imployment is about that knowledge, a ſmall portion of which to have attained is the happineſſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men: what though the tribe of <hi>Levi hath no inheritance among their brethen,</hi> ſhall not we thinke this a Royall recompenſe of that want, ſince the <hi>Lord is their inheritance,</hi> the Lord is their portion, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Lucian</hi> ſpeaks of his Preiſts, not their revenues are their, God as ſome prophane perſon might invert the words &amp; pervert the meaning, like them whom the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reproves that would have <hi>gaine to be godlineſſe,</hi> which he corrects affirming that <hi>godlineſſe is great gaine,</hi> ſo here God is their revenues: let other profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſions pleaſe themſelves in the gaine or glory
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22565:29"/>that they procure, <hi>Dat Galenus opes, dat Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianus honores,</hi> I envy them not: but let my Soule <hi>delight in the law of the Lord and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate therein day and night,</hi> and let me alway account that the chiefe part of my bleſſednes: <hi>Prayſe the Lord ye houſe of Iſrael, for in Jury is the Lord known, he hath given his ſtatutes to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:</hi> great is the priviledge of the Jew, for them did the Lord betruſt with his <hi>Oracles:</hi> but eſpecially <hi>prayſe the Lord ye houſe of</hi> Aaron, <hi>prayſe the Lord ye houſe of</hi> Levi, whom he hath entertained into neerer ſervice: though your condition be full of difficulties and your vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation obnoxious to the obloquies of the world, ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>The lots have faln to me in pleaſant places, yea I have a faire heritage:</hi> and this may be the firſt ground of thankfulnes, in a word plainly, that God hath honored us with ſuch a calling in which we have liberty and meanes to ſtudy for that which all deſire, the Art of Happineſſe:</p>
               <p>The ſecond is from this, that God affords ſo many meanes unto us to furniſh us for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this calling, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that the name of <hi>God</hi> may be even and ſquare and perfect to all due performances, you all know and have heard often how <hi>Plato</hi> than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the Gods that he was borne a Graecian, an Athenian, and eſpecially in the time of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates:</hi> and you can all make the application without my helpe, that you have greater cauſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22565:29"/>to thank God that you are born Chriſtians in the wombe of the true Church, that you are brought up Athenians in the boſom of a moſt famous Univerſity, and that in this flouriſhing eſtate of Religion, and time of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, when God hath powred forth of his Spirit ſo plentifully among us eſpecially in theſe places, that as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith of the neighbour villages of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Numa's</hi> time, that ſucking in the aire of that City they brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, righteouſneſſe; ſo from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflow of this place, all parts of the kingdom are full of knowledge, I wiſh I could ſay of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Piety:</hi> Behold a greater then <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> is here: even God himſelfe in his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; we are wet with the influence and dew of heaven, as <hi>Gedeons fleece,</hi> though all the region about be dry in compariſon; and againe when all about us are wet with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of affliction, we are dry and free: we are in the land that floweth with milke and hony: and though it were but a wilderneſſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, yet <hi>God raining Mannah from heaven the food of Angels,</hi> in that reſpect it were a mappe of heaven: we ſit under our vines every man, and under our figtrees: and are planted in Paradiſe neere the tree of life, plainly, we injoy all bleſſed meanes for the knowledge of the way to Salvation in the practicall ſtudy of Divinity: and of that knowledge which was ſo dainty heretofore we have Gods plenty:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:22565:30"/>Silver is like duſt, and gold like ſtones in our ſtreets, the moſt pretious treaſures of divine wiſdome and underſtanding are open un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us: And have we not as good cauſe to thanke God as <hi>Plato</hi> had? The <hi>Queen of She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> came from the <hi>South to heare the wiſdome of Solomon,</hi> and accounted <hi>his men happy, and thoſe his ſervants happy that ſtood ever before him and heard it: Behold a greater then</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>is here even the Spirit of God,</hi> teaching us in the doctrine of <hi>Divinity,</hi> the way of life and happineſſe: <hi>Bleſſed are your eyes that ſee and your eares that heare theſe things: Yea bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God that hath given us theſe meanes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities: Deus nobis haec otia fecit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I paſſe to the ſecond <hi>exhortation</hi> which ſhall be to the <hi>diligent ſtudy of this Doctrine</hi> and <hi>uſe of the meanes thereunto:</hi> becauſe there I ſhall lay open better the grounds of our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and withall keep my ſelfe cloſer to the matter in hand: Now we may be provoked to alacrity and diligence in this ſtudy from ſome conſiderations out of the definitions: the ſumme of all which is the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of this doctrine above others</hi> which may appeare in three particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the <hi>Certainty of the truths</hi> conteined in it from the manner of the conveiance of them to us which I told you was by <hi>Divine Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, the <hi>Nobility of the object</hi> which as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:22565:30"/>this Art is uſually and wiſely handled, is <hi>God</hi> and divine things.</p>
               <p>Third, the <hi>neceſſity of the end,</hi> which is <hi>mans happineſſe,</hi> or <hi>Salvation:</hi> a word of each of theſe and ſo I will conclude.</p>
               <p>Firſt, of the <hi>Certainty of the truths:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all other Arts, the ſkill of which we are to attaine unto by naturall reaſon upon obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and experience are ſo uncertain for the moſt part that a man when he hath done his beſt may remaine a Sceptick or Academick: by reaſon of the weaknes of our underſtanding, proceeding from the wound of originall ſin; it is not ſo with this where we receive all our light and information from God himſelf, who being the fountaine of wiſdome not ſubject to the leaſt ignorance, and the Ocean of goodneſſe far from all malice can neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nor be deceived; and therefore the light of our knowledge being derived from his light <hi>in lumine illius videmus lumen,</hi> is pure from all darkneſſe and eclipſe of error: and as among all the delight that Mathematicks afford to the ſtudents of them, the evidence and certainty of the truths, is one great part of the witchcraft, which makes them dote with love upon them: ſo I do ſee no reaſon why in this the ſame convenience ſhould not be an effectuall argument to incourage us to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the labours of our calling with much ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity and cheerefulneſſe,</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:22565:31"/>
               <p>Second, for the <hi>Nobility of the object, God and divine things,</hi> if the Poets thought ſo highly of the ſtudy of Aſtronomy, becauſe it is occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied about the Spheares and ſtars and celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bodies, that he pronounceth the firſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors thereof and profeſſors happy:
<q>
                     <l>Felices animae quibus haec cognoſcere primum,</l>
                     <l>Inque domos ſuperas ſcandere cura fuit.</l>
                  </q> Then how happy are thoſe that are buſied in the contemplation of God himſelfe, who made the heaven and ſtars and all, for it is not onely true which the father ſaid, <hi>facilius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit ſyderum conditorem humilis pietas, quam ſyderum conditionem ſuperba curioſitas,</hi> not only <hi>facilius,</hi> but I am ſure much more <hi>feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius:</hi> this is the chiefe happineſſe (in an higher degree then here we do) which we look for in heaven as all the Schoolemen determine, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen:</hi> this is an Angelical office, for I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, their Angels behold the face of their heavenly father continually ſayth our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
               <p>Third, for the <hi>neceſſity of the end</hi> which is that <hi>one thing that is neceſſary</hi> eternall life and happines: we read in the 19. <hi>Acts.</hi> That of <hi>thoſe that beleeved many which uſed curious Arts</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>brought their books and burnt them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all men, and they counted the price of them, and found it fifty thouſand peeces of ſilver,</hi> all other Arts and books in compariſon of this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22565:31"/>are but ſuperfluous and curious: this is <hi>that one thing that is neceſſary:</hi> and if all were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther burnt as they did, or baniſht as <hi>Lycurgus</hi> did all unneceſſary trades out of <hi>Sparta,</hi> that they might be the more unneceſſary, that wee might more excell in this, the matter would not be ſo great.</p>
               <p>Fourth, I might adde to this the <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and uſe no other probation for it then the laſt commendation: for as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> hath well obſerved, as the Athenians proved themſelves the moſt ancient people, becauſe the invention of corn, that moſt neceſſary helpe for the life of man proceeded from them, ſo that Doctrine muſt needs be moſt ancient, which hath the bread of life, and is therefore moſt neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Fifth, I might commend it from the <hi>Author</hi> which I touched in the 1 condition, <hi>God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> which makes much to inflame our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons toward it: for who would be aſhamed to be <hi>Gods Scholler?</hi> Or who would not rather think himſelf highly honored? When <hi>Moſes</hi> had <hi>tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with God in the mount,</hi> his face ſhined: and ſhall not the Doctrine of <hi>Gods</hi> own mouth, make their face ſhine whom <hi>God</hi> vouchſafeth to inſtruct in it.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ô yee Prophets ſons, caſt off all impediments, and let no other imployment hinder your alacrity in this ſtudy: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the excellency of this Science, and know
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:22565:32"/>the time of your viſitation: while the Sun of proſperity ſhineth, labor whiles the harveſt of the Goſpell laſteth, gather the ſheaves unto the barn that winter find not you unprovided:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q> When the Emperor paſſing through <hi>Jury,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the Land a goodly land, but without culture and tillage through the lazines of the people, he cryed out; <hi>O marcomanni, ô Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matae, ô Qua di &amp;c.</hi> O lazy Germans, I have found a people more lazy then you: take heed this be not ſaid of you, that <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> ſaid of them; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: that foole hath a price in his hand, but he hath no heart to uſe it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>be diligent therefore in reading the word of God,</hi> ſay with <hi>David, thy word O Lord is more ſweet unto me than hony, and more pretious than gold; Deſiderabilia ſuper aurum pretioſum multum,</hi> as the old tranſlation hath it in the 19. Pſal. <hi>aut multum aurum aut multum preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſum, aut multum deſiderabilia tum multum hoc haeretico parum,</hi> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> gloſſes upon the variety of the conſtruction.</p>
               <p>Second, <hi>Be diligent in hearing the word of God:</hi> let every word be pretious unto thee, and let not one of them fall to the ground. O how rich, how ſoon would this divine huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry make us:</p>
               <p>Third, <hi>Be diligent in prayer:</hi> the father
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:22565:32"/>ſaid he got more by Prayer than by ſtudy, 'tis moſt true in this Art: if thou want <hi>wiſdome,</hi> faith <hi>James, ask it of God: the ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt: this knowledge is better gotten by praying to God, then prying into Schoolemen:</p>
               <p>And to conclude, alway remember that this is a Practicall Art, and requires not knowing but doing: bare and naked ſpeculation is the tree of knowledge, that bears nothing but the apple of ſtrife betweene us, and God, and death: Practiſe, Practiſe is the tree of Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Diſtribution of Divinity.</head>
               <p>HAving already diſpatched the definition of Divinity, with ſuch incident obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as I thought fitteſt to raiſe from thence, the threed of method leads me by the hand to the diſtribution therof, to which I think I may not unfitly accommodate that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Maxim of Machiavellian policy, <hi>Divide &amp; Regna,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:22565:33"/>and rule and ſay to the beſt Divines not abuſing it, but alluding to it, <hi>Divide &amp; Regna,</hi> divide Divinity, and be King of Divines: di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it and I will warrant you Maſter of your. Art: theſe knots of diviſions, are <hi>nodi Gordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani,</hi> that portend an Empire, as you heard in another caſe: this Argument of Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Royall Argument as <hi>Plato</hi> cals it, profeſſing alſo that if he could meet with ſuch a Captaine or leader that had the ſkill of dividing aright, he would follow him as ſome God: and for this Art eſpecially I would think my ſelfe happy to be his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion: my purpoſe was to have repreſented unto you a veiw, a Synopſis of Theology and to have taken ſome more then common paines in the contriving thereof by reaſon of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe it might have yeelded, and the great variety which you ſhall finde among au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: and withall to have examined ſome of the moſt received forms, where I judge them defective: for the maine I continue ſtill in the ſame mind, but I ſhall not do it ſo fully as I thought.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe of the <hi>difficulty,</hi> it being the higheſt pitch and laſt point of all in an art, to digeſt the precepts and parts into method, and ſuppoſing an exact inquiſition and certain determination of all particular truths, as you know out of Logick: but for my ſelfe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I am but a Scholler to ſearch, not a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22565:33"/>to teach authentically: <hi>viator,</hi> not <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſor</hi> that I may allude to the Schoole di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction:</p>
               <p>Second, becauſe of the inconvenience: for if I did ſo, I ſhould be forced to hold you too long in a Scholaſticall and artificiall diſcourſe of notions, which I have done too much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and deſire now to proceed to things rather ſubſtantiall and more profitable, if not for inſtruction of knowledge at leaſt for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of practice. And therefore I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract my meditations and draw them into as narrow a compaſſe as I can: propounding only two of the moſt uſuall manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of infinite variety, and onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding them without any ſtrict ſearch made into them; and then commending a third and new (for mine owne exerciſe and yours in this inquiry) to your better conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration: becauſe being now in the entrance of this Art, and ſo in the higheſt and moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, I thinke this the fitteſt place for ſuch a proſpect, which may ſubject to your eyes the particulars: but very brieflly becauſe I would not ſeeme to lodge you like ſtrangers over the porch or entry, but like <hi>the houſhold of Faith, Domeſticifidei,</hi> as the Apoſtle cals them, and of Divinity likewiſe, in the inner and more remote roomes, according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Ancient, which you ſhall obſerve in <hi>Homer</hi> were ſtrangers, are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:22565:34"/>but the houſholders <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The firſt that I mention ſhall be that of M. <hi>Perkins,</hi> and <hi>Tilenus,</hi> and <hi>Soh nius,</hi> and other learned Divines, who divide Theolgoy into two parts:</p>
               <p>The firſt of which treats <hi>de Deo,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond, <hi>de actionibus Dei,</hi> which they proſequute proportionably in the particulars, Which I will paſſe over that I may keepe my promiſed brevity, and the rather becauſe it is eaſie for you to be fully informed of them: and that I may not ſtand to examine this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately; I thinke you may know my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning it ſufficiently, out of that which I ſaid in the definition, explaning whether and by what right God may come to be handled in Divinity: where I ſhewed that in the method of Art he was not, but in the method of Prudence he might profitably, which ground there laid being now granted, this Diſtribution will fall to the ground of it ſelfe without any more a do.</p>
               <p>This obſervation onely I will now adde, that though that diviſion be not according to the rule of Art, yet many actions of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed come to be conſidered in this Doctrine, namely, ſuch as, without which man cannot attaine to his laſt end and happines, to which this rule guides: for there are ſome immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate actions of God, as for example <hi>Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:22565:34"/>and all the actions even of man, are in ſome ſort actions of God being performed by the help of his Spirit and aſſiſtance of his grace, without which they cannot be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: inſomuch that <hi>Durands</hi> puts this for an objection that Divinity is not a practicall Art becauſe theſe actions are not wholy ours, nor in our power alone to perform: and in this ſenſe I deny not, but the actions of God are handled in Divinity ſo far as they tend to mans happineſſe: but this helps that diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution but a little.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe that comprehends under it the nature of God and attributes, which make the firſt part, not only his actions.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe it extends it ſelfe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actions beſide thoſe that conferre to the fornamed ſcope of mans happines, both which reſpects ſhew it to bee of too much genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</p>
               <p>And thridly, therefore that which belongs properly to this doctrine is but a ſmall portion in that diſtribution, and thoſe actions of God which are neceſſary may well be ranked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another order: many other exceptions I might bring againſt that diviſion if it would ſtand with my purpoſe, but I omit them both for that reaſon, and becauſe they ſhall better appeare out of that which follows.</p>
               <p>The ſecond that I will name, ſhall be that which <hi>Ramus,</hi> as I think, firſt obſerved, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:22565:35"/>
                  <hi>Polanus</hi> after him hath much confirmed, and many modern divines approve and follow, which makes two parts of Theology,</p>
               <p>Firſt, of Faith <hi>de fide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, <hi>de fidei operibus</hi> of good works, the firſt <hi>de credendis,</hi> the ſecond <hi>de faciendis,</hi> and ſo forward in all the ſubdiviſions: and this I confeſſe I thought abſolute a long time both for the commendation of good authors, as alſo for the conſanguinity with the Scripture and congruity with Reaſon, till that upon better conſideration I found it did not ſatisfy me.</p>
               <p>For firſt, beſide the ambiguity of the word <hi>fides</hi> which cannot be avoided if it be taken in that infinite extent to comprehend ſo much and ſo divers things in it as it muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity according to that diſtribution, all which cannot poſſibly be conceived to agree in one univocall praedication or formall reſpect, as I might eaſily demonſtrate: but are brought under it, not without apparent force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, beſide the ſeeming agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the parts one with another againſt the nature and rule of a diſtribution which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires they ſhould be oppoſite; which though it may be well anſwered, yet in my opininon were better avoided: for it ſounds harſh and ſeems unreaſonable that one part ſhould treat of the habit another of the act of faith: and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:22565:35"/>whereas it may be ſaid for that, that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it is not to oppoſe and ſever the habit of faith from the formall effects of it, for that would be abſurd indeed: but by <hi>opera fidei</hi> you muſt underſtand other graces and virtues, ſo that the oppoſition ſtands between the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of <hi>faith,</hi> and the habit of them <hi>graces</hi> and <hi>virtues</hi> which are therefore called the <hi>works of faith,</hi> or <hi>effects;</hi> becauſe beſide their owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per habits from whence they proceed <hi>formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tèr,</hi> they muſt and doe alſo in ſome ſort flow from faith, and from it they have all their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and acceptation with <hi>God,</hi> being without it but <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi> as you all have heard out of <hi>Auſtin</hi> often: for <hi>without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul:</hi> but this is not enough if to excuſe it, yet not to juſtifie it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the terms are ſo ambiguous that they give too much occaſion to miſtakes and ſtumbling, as I ſaid before.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe in ſanctification, which they that propound this diſtribution range under faith, the habits of all other graces and virtues are infuſed, and ſo included as well as of Faith.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe in the Decalogue, the rule of obedience and good works, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently a principall portion of the ſecond part, faith is alſo included or elſe other worſe inconveniences will follow: and ſo there is a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:22565:36"/>mutuall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and immeation in theſe parts, as Divines ſpeake in another caſe, which cannot be without a ſtrange and wonderfull confuſion: in which regard I cannot ſee that theſe parts are artificially and accurately cut out: but beſide that which hath been alledged I could produce many more exceptions which I omit rather: and in both theſe I would be thus underſtood, not as rejecting ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as unprofitable: for I approve them both as very good though not exact: and ſtand not much upon formalities of Art, ſo as they comprehend in them the ſubſtance of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall truths: preferring this before the other as I would preferre a peece of gold for weight rather then for workmanſhip, for value rather then for elegancy, like that French coyne in the hiſtorian that in <hi>qua plus formae quam pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris.</hi> And now give me leave to commend a third a new form of this Art to your conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration with two cautions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I do not think that I can ſee further, or go beyond thoſe ancient Heroes in Divinity, who were ſo richly furniſhed with underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which they ſo thriftily improved by incomparable paines and induſtry: that is far from my meaning, but only as I ſaid, to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe my ſelfe and you in this inquiry: and yet ye know what the Philoſopher ſaith, that there is an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an increaſe and growth in all Arts: And the common ſaying is <hi>diſcipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:22565:36"/>eſt prioris poſterior dies: Day unto day ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth ſpeech, and night unto night ſheweth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt: and though a Gyant be taller then a Pygme, yet a Pygme upon his ſhoulders hath advantage of him, though ancient ſurpaſſe modern times, yet we plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their heifer may underſtand their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, and with their helpe may outſtrip them: in a word it is with the light of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as with the lamps at the games in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, one generation caries it as far as it can, and after it, doth <hi>tradere lampada,</hi> to the ſucceeding generation, which runs along further with it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I do not imagine that which I am to propound abſolute, though compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively I prefer it, or produce it rather ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to give ſome further light to theſe dark paſſages, or at leaſt ſome illuſtration to that which hath been ſaid already by others:</p>
               <p>Thirdly, though for the generall I hope <hi>I</hi> ſhall inſiſt in the right way, yet for the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars <hi>I</hi> do not intend them, as full or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, neither much leſſe will <hi>I</hi> contend they are ſo: for <hi>I</hi> could not hope to ſatisfie my ſelf in them on the ſodaine, and therefore content my ſelfe to propound them, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the Philoſopher ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>Now that <hi>I</hi> may proceed according to the nature of method, which deduceth one axiom one precept out of another: for it is there as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:22565:37"/>you ſee it in ſpinning, the lock of wool is firſt faſtned upon the ſpindle, and out of that the threed is drawn in a long ſeries, and then an hint of that is left to which the next is faſtned, till all be done in like manner: ſo in an Art, firſt, the Definition is laid down, out of which muſt be ſpun, and drawn all the ſucceeding precepts: and thus <hi>I</hi> will do with this: the Definition then you may remember to have been this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Divinity is a Doctrine of mans happineſſe:</hi> there be two words which note the <hi>ſubjectum formale, Happineſſe;</hi> and the <hi>ſubjectum materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale, Man;</hi> and according to theſe two, <hi>I</hi> frame the <hi>Diſtribution</hi> thus:</p>
               <p>Firſt, of <hi>Happines</hi> ſimply conſidered.</p>
               <p>Secondly, of <hi>Happines</hi> in the <hi>Subject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, of <hi>Happines in generall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, of <hi>Happines in particular,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the divers ſtates of it <hi>in relation to the Subject:</hi> to illuſtrate this I will put you in minde of three other diſtributions which harpe upon this, though they doe not fully agree.</p>
               <p>The firſt is of ſome that conſidering Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to be <hi>medicina animarum,</hi> borrow termes from the Phyſick of the body which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate to this, and part it proportion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly into <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of mans <hi>miſery</hi> by nature, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of his <hi>recovery</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from which the common method in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rfin</hi> differs
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:22565:37"/>but little: this ſuppoſeth mans fall or begins with it, and therefore I think either omitteth ſomething neceſſary, or elſe incurreth a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary confuſion of thoſe things which would better be more diſtinctly handled.</p>
               <p>The ſecond I find in a learned Author <hi>Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in his preface upon the ſentences, who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides it into <hi>Theologia prima,</hi> that treats of <hi>man</hi> in his firſt <hi>eſtate of integrity,</hi> and <hi>Theologia ſecunda,</hi> that conſiders him after his <hi>fall,</hi> as to be guided to his happines; and this comes a degree neerer to that I propounded than the former, becauſe it mentions both eſtates and handles them, and yet it ſeemes ſhort by one degree.</p>
               <p>The third comes up yet cloſer, and you ſhall find it in <hi>Trelcatius,</hi> who divides Divinity thus: there be two parts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>de cauſis Salutis noſtrae eoque de Dei operibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>de Subjecto illius id eſt Homine, varioque Hominis ſtatu:</hi> and explaning the ground of this diſtribution in the next words, he ſpeakes for my purpoſe more directly: <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quae Theologiae finis proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus eſt, duobus modis conſideratur, tum in ſe &amp; cauſis ſuis ſimpliciter, tum Relate ad Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ad quod ordinata eſt, qua ratione variè mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dificatur, pro conditione Subjecti multiplici in quo eſt:</hi> where ye ſee ye have the ſame diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of that <hi>I</hi> gave, and in the ſame forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:22565:38"/>of termes almoſt: and this ſuperads a degree to the former which I think is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               <p>The firſt takes <hi>man</hi> as he is now <hi>faln,</hi> and ſo applies meanes for recovery of his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</p>
               <p>The ſecond conſiders, both of his <hi>ſtanding</hi> firſt, and then his <hi>fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This third abſtracts, what is common to both eſtates, what is the common <hi>nature of his happineſſe,</hi> and ſo deſcends to the particular accommodation thereof, according to the difference of his condition: and this I think is full enough and large in extent, to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all things that this Doctrine is to meddle with: and I will uſe no other reaſon to prove it, becauſe I think it carries ſome evidence of truth or at leaſt probability with it, eſpecially ſuppoſing the grounds formerly laid, but only that it is drawn out of the definition with ſuch facility, that it appeares to be a naturall diſtribution: the doctrine of mans happines hath two parts.</p>
               <p>Firſt of <hi>Happineſſe in it ſelfe in generall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>of mans happineſſe,</hi> in reference to the proper ſubject: and now I proceed to ſome few principall ſubdiviſions to give you a view and <hi>Synopſis</hi> of the whole Art.</p>
               <p>Happineſſe in generall hath two things in it to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the <hi>parts or degrees,</hi> or affections, for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:22565:38"/>I deſire you to remember that I am not curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for termes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>kinds of happineſſe:</hi> the parts or degrees are two.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of it, or <hi>Habituall happineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>Continuation</hi> of it, or <hi>Actuall happineſſe:</hi> the former I briefly touched the laſt time; the latter I conceive to conſiſt in two things eſpecially.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the gracious <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of all things without a man by God, <hi>in ordine ad fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitatem:</hi> for it is impoſſible that man ſhould <hi>natare ſine cortice,</hi> and attaine to his own <hi>ſuo marti,</hi> by his own endeavors, without Gods providence ſupporting him, and ſuggeſting all neceſſaries to him, there being the ſame proportion between him and God in this caſe that there is between inferior creatures and man: and therefore as it is in architecture and ſuch like Arts, which in regard of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aptitude of the ſubject may be ſpeculative, but in regard of the Artificer, whoſe actions muſt paſſe upon it to bring their <hi>potentia</hi> to <hi>actus,</hi> their poſſibilities to perfection, are Practicall: ſo or not much unlike in divinity, it is Practicall moſt in regard of God: as I noted in part before:</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing, for the <hi>continuation of Happines,</hi> the <hi>virtuous and religious operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man;</hi> which by the helpe of the former
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:22565:39"/>the <hi>grace of God:</hi> he is able to produce, in which reſpect <hi>Divinity</hi> is alſo properly Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call on mans part, as hath been ſaid; theſe are the two things which I call the continuation or the <hi>fluxus</hi> of happines, the <hi>Operation of Gods grace toward man,</hi> and the <hi>grace of mans O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration toward God:</hi> for habituall happineſſe ſtanding moſt, as I ſaid, in the <hi>relation recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> of <hi>God to man</hi> being his God, and <hi>man to God</hi> being his ſervant, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and act of it muſt needs be placed in the reflexion of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all offices of love, according to the peculiar condition of either: And now follow the kinds of happineſſe, which are two.</p>
               <p>Firſt, of <hi>this life;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second, <hi>of the life to come:</hi> in the former according to that which hath been ſaid there be two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> which is in a certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of our <hi>union with God,</hi> and conſequently fruition of all good, far inferior to the ſecond eſtate which is future:</p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>Continuation,</hi> which is,</p>
               <p>Firſt by the <hi>gracious providence of God,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying all things neceſſary for ſuch an eſtate, and enabling us to action agreeing to his will.</p>
               <p>Secondly, our <hi>Religious action</hi> being thus enabled, which is of two ſorts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, our <hi>generall worſhip of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, our <hi>ſpeciall:</hi> the generall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:22565:39"/>of God is in the obſervation and of his will and gracious covenant which he pleaſes to make with man: where two things are to be noted.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Subſtance of the Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>Seales:</hi> the Subſtance in two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to <hi>love and honor God</hi> above all things for himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>to love other things</hi> reſpectively <hi>in ſubordination to God:</hi> and in theſe three are divers particulars, but I muſt leave them here.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Seales</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> are ſenſible things, applyed according to the condition of mans nature, who is both <hi>intellectuall</hi> and <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive;</hi> the uſe of which according to Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution ſhould both confirme the promiſes on Gods part, and as it were ingage him to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, and confirme man in his duty, and as it were oblige him more to the performance of it: the ſpeciall worſhip of God is in <hi>prayer, thanksgiving, praiſing</hi> of his glorious name, and the like: and this is <hi>the happines of this life:</hi> the happines of the life to come is that ſtate which God is pleaſed voluntarily and freely to promiſe to man; where be two things like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> which far ſurpaſſeth the former, man being to be elevated above himſelfe in ſupernaturall perfections.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:22565:40"/>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>Continuation,</hi> firſt, in Gods ſingular and immutable Grace, ſecondly, by the operations of man, more noble and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to ſuch a glorious eſtate: and (which I ſhould have mentioned before) theſe two are ſubordinate, the former to the latter: inſomuch that this is called happines by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation and excellency; the other, but the way and means to this Happines among the moſt of our Divines. And all theſe come to be handled in the firſt part of Divinity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Happines</hi> in generall, becauſe they belong indifferently to man in all eſtates: out of which the ſecond part with ſome inflexion, may be eaſily conceived: and therefore I come to that:</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of Divinity is concerning <hi>Happines in ſpeciall,</hi> in reference to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>Man;</hi> who muſt be conſidered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in the <hi>ſtate of integrity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, in the ſtate of the <hi>fall and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> in integrity,</p>
               <p>Firſt, the <hi>conſtitution of his happineſſe,</hi> was (in one word) the <hi>Image of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>continuation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, in <hi>Gods grace</hi> giving all things meet, for upholding that eſtate.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>mans obſervance</hi> in the worſhip of God, firſt generall, ſecondly ſpeciall.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Generall for the covenant, firſt the <hi>Subſtance</hi> as it was.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:22565:40"/>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Morall</hi> in theſe two things, firſt to <hi>love God</hi> above all as a creator, ſecondly, all other ſubordinately.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Ceremoniall,</hi> abſtaining from the forbidden fruit of the tree of knowledge of good and evill, ſecondly for the Seale of the Covenant, which was then the tree of life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for <hi>ſpeciall worſhip</hi> it was prayer &amp;c, the propiety of which was, that it might be, without a mediator:</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Future life was an elevation above that naturall eſtate to a better, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to that we look for in Chriſt: and this for the firſt eſtate of integrity:</p>
               <p>The ſecond for the <hi>Fall,</hi> in regard of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life is mixt and worſe then the former: and firſt for ſubſtance is the ſame alway, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for circumſtance different:</p>
               <p>The <hi>ſubſtance</hi> firſt for <hi>conſtitution</hi> muſt be beſtowed wholly by God, and that by a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble act, firſt of <hi>Redemption</hi> by the Sonne, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly of <hi>Sanctification</hi> by the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>continuation,</hi> firſt by the <hi>grace of God,</hi> in Chriſt, ſecondly by the <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of man</hi> guided by the Spirit: which are,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Obſervation of the new covenant</hi> in a mediator, whereof firſt, the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> is in two things, firſt to <hi>love God</hi> above all things in Chriſt, 2. <hi>all other things for Chriſt,</hi> ſecondly the <hi>Seales</hi> are all repreſentative of Chriſt: and ſecondly <hi>Prayer</hi> to be put up in the <hi>name of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:22565:41"/>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>mediator:</hi> and this is the ſubſtance, the ſumme.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, this is <hi>varied in circumſtance, of Chriſt;</hi> firſt <hi>promiſed,</hi> ſecondly <hi>performed,</hi> where the chiefe difference is in regard of the outward parts of the Sacraments, and the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies: and this is the ſtate of this preſent life: the future life is not onely paſſing the preſent, but alſo that future which <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have been exalted to in the ſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, as Divines think, becauſe in it concur both the <hi>free gift of God,</hi> willing to advance us, and the <hi>merit of Chriſt</hi> purchaſing it, and a congruity that the humane nature being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the incomparable dignity of the hypoſtaticall union in Chriſt the head, ſhould bee proportionably dignified in the whole kinde.</p>
               <p>I know I muſt looke for many objections which I ſhould incounter withall concerning the order of the generall, and the inſufficiency of the particulars: but <hi>I</hi> will not incomber my ſelfe and you with a long anſwer; only in briefe <hi>I</hi> ſay,</p>
               <p>Firſt, if the generall mold and frame be convenient, that is as much as <hi>I</hi> aime at, the particular paſſages <hi>I</hi> ſtand not much upon.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is no wonder if many Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall things may ſeem to be wanting; for my purpoſe was to touch only <hi>ſumma rerum faſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia,</hi> not to deſcend to all inferior parts.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:22565:41"/>
               <p>Thirdly, you muſt remember there may be a great difference between Divinity, as it is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually handled, and as it ſhould be exactly; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the method of prudence and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Art: the latter <hi>I</hi> would willingly find, becauſe it keepeth cloſeſt to the nature of the Object to be regulated: the former notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>I</hi> will be content to follow, and <hi>I</hi> thinke is beſt abſolutely, all things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as <hi>I</hi> am ſure it is more uſuall and more uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and among all thoſe methods, as <hi>I</hi> eaſily diſlike none eſpecially thoſe two that <hi>I</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the beginning: ſo <hi>I</hi> moſt approve that of <hi>Trelcatius</hi> which premiſeth two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Cognitionis,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> which is <hi>God:</hi> and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to the parts, becauſe it comes neereſt to the accurate method in generall: though in many particulars <hi>I</hi> prefer either of the other two before it. <hi>I</hi> will now in a word commend unto you the uſe of that which ye have heard, from whence you ſhall perceive my ſcope in this delineation: I confeſſe I have done it ſo rudely and rawly, that it may bee rather a meanes to breed a loathing, than a liking of Divinity: as <hi>Socrates</hi> to beat down the pride of <hi>Alcibiades</hi> (as <hi>Aelian</hi> tels the ſtory) which the opinion of his great poſſeſſions had bred in him, ſhewing him a map of Greece, bid him find out his land if he could, but when hee
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:22565:42"/>could not, ſaid thus to him, and are not you aſhamed then, to be proud of thoſe lands, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: ſo may ſome man thinke the worſe of the rich poſſeſſion of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, becauſe in the little map that <hi>I</hi> have drawn many parcels are not to be found, and as <hi>Tully</hi> ſayth of hangings, or ſuch like, ſo long as they are folded together and wraped, there is no ſight of them, nothing that may draw liking or wonder: ſo long as theſe Divine truths are folded and plighted together in theſe few diviſions, there is no luſtre or light ſparkles from them, that may inflame the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder with love towards them; but if they were opened and diſplayed <hi>mirabiles amores excitarent ſui:</hi> yet my purpoſe was, becauſe I cannot go through all, at leaſt to give you a light a far off; as the tempter led our Savior into an high mountaine whence he ſhewed him all the Kingdomes of the earth, the glory of which might intice him; ſo have I preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you a view of all divinity to incite you to a love and ſtudy of them: But why do I uſe ſuch a compariſon: rather as the Lord caried <hi>Moſes</hi> into mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> whence he ſaw the <hi>holy land</hi> though he could not enter into it: ſo becauſe I cannot lead you into the poſſeſſion of this holy land, I have at leaſt lent you a proſpect of it: I might out of all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſingle out ſome more excellent peeces to kindle your affections, but I muſt omit it: and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:22565:42"/>end with this counſell; that every one that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the ſtudy of Divinity, would indeavor to get and hold <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Paul</hi> advertiſeth <hi>Timothy, a form of wholſome words,</hi> for the ſingular utility that it will bring to him: firſt in regard of his memory, which is wonderfully helped by this, as you al know, though I ſpare to tell you: both out of your firſt principles of Art, as alſo by experience: And he that carries about with him in his head a frame of Divinity, ſhall have a ſafe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, where to repoſe all ſcattered and looſe notions that he heares or reads, the ſeverall branches of it ſhall be like ſo many borders of herbs, ſo many beds of flowers, ſo many boxes of ſpices, in which he may meet with them againe upon all occaſions.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in regard of <hi>Judgement</hi> which is much ſtrengthened and backed by this: for this will furniſh him with the moſt principall things of the Art, which he ſhall behold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one, ſo that he may compare them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and examine them at his pleaſure: and as in a map a man may ſee places how they are ſituat for North and South or the like, and what diſtance there is from place to place, may eaſily be meaſured: ſo in ſuch a frame, or tipe, a man may behold what agreement or diſtance there is between one thing and another in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity: how one thing borders upon another &amp;c. without any difficulty, and this reduced
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:22565:43"/>to uſe will appeare better either in a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, which will receive much light, the doubtfull truth being reduced to his proper ſeat, and there examined and decided by ſome infallible truths: and ſo in the explication of a place of Scripture according as a man hath made a plat forme of Divinity familiar to him; ſo will he expedite himſelfe better or worſe according as it is: for it will direct him how to conceive of a trope or proper ſignfication of a word; and ſo in other caſes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and laſtly for <hi>invention,</hi> this will furniſh him with an inexhauſt treaſury of matter ſpringing from the conference of one portion with another; but will be moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall, for the diſcovery of two arguments moſt neceſſary, the <hi>Genera</hi> I meane, which will appeare out of the <hi>Series,</hi> and the Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions which will be as ſuccinct and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous in ſuch an order, as you ſee they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and tedions without it: a <hi>Divine</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this cannot chuſe but have all his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſnared and intangled, as if he were in a labyrinth without a clue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:22565:43"/>
               <head>Of the Happineſſe of <hi>MAN. CHAP. III.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY purpoſe was, according to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod that is commonly received and practiſed among the beſt Artiſts in the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Arts, immediately after the definition of Divinity explaned, to have proceeded to the diſtribution: becauſe I deſire to make haſte out of theſe Scholaſticall and notionall truths, to ſuch things as may be more practicall and profitable: but the time approching, and the duties to be then performed by us, putting me in mind, I will alter my courſe a little, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect my ſpeech ſo, that if it be not every way ſutable, which my generall project would not permit, yet I hope it ſhall not be altogether unſeaſonable: though it concerne not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Sacrament in particular, yet it ſhall in generall concerne matters of practiſe and uſe: though it direct not receivers in a peculiar manner, yet it ſhall not ſtand Sholars only in hand (as perhaps the other doth) but every Chriſtian in their meaſure to know and doe: for I meane to ſpeake of the <hi>Happines of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:22565:44"/>man,</hi> wherein it conſiſts: and though I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have interpoſed the diſtribution and Synopſis of Divinity between the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and this, as I ſaid, yet as he in <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaid more prittily then piouſly; when he threw at a dog, but hit his ſtepmother, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo I may ſay: for if I had continued in my firſt reſolution for my method, I ſhould have <hi>gone forth by the footſteps of the ſtocke, and fed my kids, by the tents of other ſhepheards,</hi> as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour counſels his Spouſe, in the firſt of the Canticles, I ſhould not have ſtraid a whit out of the common road: but as I have now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered it, I think I ſhall gaine this advantage, to go the neereſt way, according to the exact pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of Art; for by the ſame reaſon that <hi>I</hi> thought it probable, before that the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of art in generall ariſes from the <hi>Object,</hi> it being in it ſelf ſpecially indiviſible, &amp; the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of precepts in the ſame Art ariſes from the multiplicity and variety of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall branches of ſome particular object: I think it will follow by good conſequence, that the Diſtribution of an Art will follow the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of his object: the Art it ſelfe being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, but by accident in reference to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, with which it goes along: even as Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick would be perhaps not more truely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the matter is the ſame, but more truly (as we ſay) in formality, be ordered thus, if it were defined <hi>Dialectica eſt Ars rationis: Ratio
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:22565:44"/>eſt ſimplex vel Compoſita,</hi> ſo that you ſhould underſtand the object primarily to beare the diviſion, which ſhould notwithſtanding ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily redound to the Art it ſelfe, with which that is linked in ſo neer a conjunction: but thus much by the way, onely upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the alteration of that method, which I firſt propounded to my ſelf: I come now to the point, I meane to proſequte, namely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Happineſſe of man:</hi> wherein, that I may proceed with leaſt offence and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition,</p>
               <p>I will firſt <hi>premiſe</hi> ſome few obſervations unfolding the ambiguities of ſome terms, that occur in this argument, and may otherwiſe breed ſome obſcurity in the matter:</p>
               <p>And then ſecondly, I will deliver the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall things to be known, in two concluſions or aſſertions: for the firſt I will name three onely, and that very briefly.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> may be taken two wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for <hi>Bonum praeſtantiſſimum</hi> and <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulare,</hi> which excels and ſurpaſſes all other in compariſon, and that is ſome one particular good, which is exalted above his fellows, to the higheſt degree of eminency.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for <hi>Bonum integrum</hi> or <hi>univerſale</hi> which is a collection of all the particulars, comprehended under the Spheare or latitude of <hi>bonum,</hi> and therefore called <hi>ſummum,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:22565:45"/>all being ranked according to methods heraldry, that ſits in the higheſt place, that juſtly challenges the precedency: to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate this to our preſent purpoſe, in the firſt acception, God is ſaid, and moſt truly to be <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> for to whom <hi>will yee liken mee,</hi> ſaith the Lord in the Prophet, or what may compare with God, as it is in the Pſalme: but in the ſecond meaning it is not ſo, neither is it any one particular that can claime that name, but it is a confluence and concurrence of all together that makes <hi>ſummum bonum:</hi> the uſe of this diſtinction ſhall appeare by and by.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you muſt diſtinguiſh between <hi>Summum Bonum</hi> taken in either of the former ſenſes, and <hi>Beatitudo,</hi> as <hi>Polanus</hi> doth: the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conſideration is of good things, barely &amp; abſolutely, as ſo in themſelves, the latter beſide that, is reſpective and includes an habitude in which they ſtand to man, who injoies them: or as the Schoolemen have it, in other words there is a double <hi>beatitude, objectiva,</hi> the ſame that <hi>ſummu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and that is God, as it is taken for <hi>praeſtantiſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or a collection of all, in a word, <hi>humanum bonum,</hi> according to the other ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, and ſecondly <hi>formalis,</hi> the ſame that I cal'd <hi>beatitudo</hi> in propriety, as diſtinct from <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> and that is, either that operation by which we have union with the <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> and injoy it, as they ſay com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:22565:45"/>or that habit or ſtate as I rather think from whence a man hath the denomination of Happineſſe, or both, for both of neceſſity muſt be conceived.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, you muſt obſerve a triple latitude in the ſignification of this word <hi>Happines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, in the largeſt ſenſe, the fruition of any good, being a portion of it, doth alſo get the name of <hi>happineſſe,</hi> and he is at large an happy man, who injoyes any ſuch particular good, and ſo we uſe to ſay occaſionally, hearing of any good befals any man, he is an happy man, ſo far namely as that will extend, for otherwiſe the ſame man may want many things, and be ſimply to ſay, very miſerable.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the ſtricteſt ſenſe that is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe only that ariſes from a confluence of all humane good, and he onely deſerves the name in whom they all meet and are married; and thus no man upon earth, is or ſhall bee happy.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in a middle ſenſe, that is happines where the fruition of good, though not free from all mixture of evill; yet is ſo prevalent &amp; predominant, that it may juſtly denominate a man happy ſimply, though not ſimply hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in all reſpect, and that man is happy where this is to be found: this laſt you may call out of the Schoolmen <hi>eſſentiall happineſſe and true,</hi> the ſecond <hi>integrall and compleat happineſſe,</hi> the third for diſtinctions ſake if you will, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:22565:46"/>and incompleat Happineſſe: I might add ſomething alſo of true and falſe happineſſe, ſound and ſuppoſed, but the homonymie is ſo palpable that I ſhall not need, and therefore will content my ſelfe with that which hath been ſaid already of the firſt point, reſerving other things that may ſeeme to be of moment and conſequence to their proper oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and paſſe now to the ſecond part I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, which was to ſhew, what happines is, and wherein it conſiſts in two concluſions, and that according to the two ſtricter acceptions of the word even now mentioned.</p>
               <p>The firſt ſhall declare what <hi>integrall and compleat happineſſe</hi> is, and wherein it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts.</p>
               <p>The ſecond what <hi>true and eſſentiall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is, and wherein it conſiſts: the firſt I will diſpatch briefly meaning to inſiſt moſt upon the latter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Compleat happineſſe,</hi> I call that where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is defective, and you may conceive it, I think tolerably, by ſuch a diſcription or a like. <hi>Happineſſe is a perfect eſtate of a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable nature wherein it injoys all good that is due unto it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I deſcribe it by <hi>eſtate</hi> rather then Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe no operation doth denominate the efficient, but happines doth the ſubject: again every operation is tranſient, and in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall flux, but happineſſe ſeemes to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:22565:46"/>permanent: and thirdly operation doth never perfectly exiſt: but happines doth: otherwiſe, that of <hi>Solon</hi> ſhould be true which the Philoſopher rejects, <hi>Ante obitum nemo ſupremaque funera foelix:</hi> and a man ſhould not be happy till he were not at all.</p>
               <p>Secondly I adde a <hi>perfect ſtate,</hi> which needs no further explication.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I ſay of a <hi>reaſonable creature:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as <hi>Scaliger</hi> well taxes <hi>Cardan,</hi> for attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting <hi>vitam beatam muſcae quae ſane ex optimo puriſſimoque loquendi genere ſoli debetur homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni:</hi> and if the meaning be, becauſe nothing is wanting to it, <hi>non improbè ſentit ſed pluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam improbè loquitur:</hi> for that reaſon is no ſufficient appellation or warrant for that, for if we would <hi>deglubere ſignificationem,</hi> as he ſpeakes in that manner, by the ſame ambitious ſuperſtition we might call an element happy, becauſe it is in his own place, which would be <hi>nugae ſed</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, though we read in <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by a trope improperly ſo ſtiled: but whereas, as <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſeemes to appropriat happineſſe to a man, I think that is not right, neither is it his purpoſe ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine it, for an Angel may be happy even in propriety of language: and therefore ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in generall I extend it as far as it goes to all reaſonable creatures, though I intend the particular application and uſe to man only now follows the other part of the deſcription
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:22565:47"/>which ſaith it is ſuch <hi>an eſtate of the reaſonable creature, wherein it injoyes all that good which is due unto it.</hi> And this perhaps might have ſufficed alone to have deſcribed <hi>Happineſſe</hi> to have been the fruition of all good due to man, though the other make it more plaine and full; where,</p>
               <p>Firſt, by <hi>good</hi> that is due, I meane not by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny neceſſary bond or obligation in which God is tyed to the creature to give it, but that which hath proportion unto and congruity with the nature of man, and to which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man hath a naturall aptitude and appetite or propenſion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by <hi>all good</hi> I ſay, becauſe man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a compound creature muſt have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound happines of many ingredients, becauſe the perfection of the whole muſt reſult from the perfection of every part; and you may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt them thus: the good is either <hi>Summum</hi> which is God, as I ſaid; or <hi>Subordinatum,</hi> and this again is either <hi>internum</hi> within the eſſence of a man; or <hi>externum</hi> without him: <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> is either <hi>Bonum Corporis</hi> or <hi>Bonum Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae: bonum Animae</hi> is either <hi>Intellectus</hi> or <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis:</hi> or if you had rather take them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this curioſity of Art, they are five.</p>
               <p>Firſt, God and his favor, as the ſupreame Lord.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Reaſon, right</hi> and conformable to God.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:22565:47"/>
               <p>Thirdly, a <hi>will</hi> in tune and conformable to right reaſon.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, a <hi>body</hi> in good temper and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ſerviceable to a will tuned.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, <hi>outward bleſſings</hi> anſwerable to all the reſt: theſe make the ſpheare and circle of good; which, upon whoſe head ſoever they fall, doe crowne him with compleat and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect happines: which, becauſe of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded brevity, it ſhall ſuffice to have made an enumeration of, without illuſtration.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, for <hi>fruition</hi> I may conveniently and proportionably name five degrees of it: though perhaps every one of them ſhall not be judged exactly neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> and uſurpation or uſe of thoſe good (for I joyn thoſe two together) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe perhaps they cannot alway be well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in that reſpect (they have to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe) which is for the moſt part by the action of virtue, ſecondly, <hi>knowledge</hi> of that poſſeſſion, and a conſideration reflected upon our riches and happines, Thirdly <hi>delight</hi> ſpringing from that knowledge, fourthly <hi>quiet of all parts</hi> filled with that delight and ſatisfied, fiftly, <hi>ſecurity</hi> of that quiet upon <hi>aſſurance reaſonable</hi> of the continuance and perpetuity of that eſtate and thoſe good: All theſe where they meet are enough to milk out all the good that can be in them; to ſuck out all the juice and ſweetneſſe, all the marrow and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:22565:48"/>fatneſſe that they have: and the name of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity ſometimes imports ſome one of theſe, ſometime two or more, and the opinions of Philoſophers and divines accordingly pitch upon them: but where there is a concourſe of all, I cannot ſee what ſhould bee wanting: for he that hath ſuch a fruition of all good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, internall, externall, in body Soule and whole man, as brings with it a perfect quieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the naturall appetite joyned with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable delight, and unmoved ſecurity (that I may contract all into a narrow roome) <hi>Quis non illum beatum dixerit &amp; non potius beatiſſimum:</hi> I might enlarge theſe things with illuſtrations and probations if the matter required, but I think it ſo perſpicuous and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident to any that will conſider it, that it would be but loſt labour to dwell any longer upon it: eſpecially this being agreeable with that definition which you know is common out of <hi>Boetius,</hi> that <hi>Beatitudo eſt ſtatus bonorum omnium aggregatione perfectus,</hi> and that of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelm Sufficientia commodorum omnium,</hi> and that of <hi>Auſtin, Beatus eſt qui habet quicquid vult &amp; nihil mali vult</hi> as they are alleaged by <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory de Valentia:</hi> and I thinke it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon notion that preſents it ſelfe to all men, when they heare that word <hi>Happines,</hi> to think preſently upon ſome univerſall good: and he that would make an emblem or picture of happineſſe, muſt ſet it forth like that of Peace
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:22565:48"/>among the Ancients with a <hi>cornucopia</hi> an horn of plenty in the hand, or like the picture of <hi>Pan,</hi> with all ſhapes and infinite variety: and therefore according to my promiſe and deſire <hi>I</hi> will now proceed to the ſecond aſſertion which ſhall explaine what eſſentiall happineſſe is, and wherein it conſiſts: wherein I may be more punctuall, becauſe it will be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Theologicall as you ſhall perceive:</p>
               <p>Eſſentiall <hi>Happines I</hi> underſtand, which though it want many particulars, which are <hi>de integritate felicitatis,</hi> yet it hath all things that are <hi>de eſſentia,</hi> and hath enough to ſalve the name and title of happineſſe in truth and propriety: as a man that wants his arms or legs is not <hi>integer homo;</hi> but ſo long as the <hi>Soule is united to the body</hi> is a man: or, as the name being given according to the predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant part; wine doth not loſe the name of wine for a little water mingled with it: ſo here, though there be ſome wants and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſome miſery mingled with this happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet taking more of happines then miſery, it hath the name and nature of happines; and this I call <hi>eſſentiall Happines:</hi> and this I ſay muſt be placed in <hi>God alone</hi> and <hi>our fruition of him</hi> or <hi>union with him.</hi> But to handle this point more fully, as <hi>I</hi> purpoſe in the reſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to take ſome place of Scripture for a ground and foundation to build upon (where it may be done conveniently) ſo <hi>I</hi> will doe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:22565:49"/>here: and that you ſhall find in the laſt verſe of the 144 Pſalme, where ye have theſe words <hi>Bleſſed are the people that are in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord:</hi> which as you ſee, ſpeaks of bleſſednes, and as <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, couch as much of that argument, and for our preſent ſcope, as any that <hi>I</hi> could meet withall: and <hi>I</hi> am only ſorry the time is ſo ſhort that <hi>I</hi> ſhall be forced but to name the things <hi>I</hi> have to deliver, becauſe <hi>I</hi> reſolve to goe through with this point and diſpatch it at this time.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pſalme</hi> as may ſeeme, was compoſed in time of war, and is partly ſpent in a lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory thankſgiving for ſucceſſe and victory; <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord my ſtrength, which teacheth my hands to war and my fingers to fight:</hi> and partly is <hi>petitory,</hi> conteining a ſuite to God for further ſafety and deliverance from the proud enemy and war, that the Church might injoy the bleſſings of peace <hi>Bow thy heavens ô Lord and come downe, touch the mountaines and they ſhall ſmoke: that our ſons may be as plants grown up in their youth; that our daughters may be as corner ſtones poliſhed after the ſimilitude of a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace:</hi> and there having made a Catalogue of the benefits of peace, the Pſalmiſt concludes all with this <hi>Epilogue,</hi> this <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>patheticall Epiphonema; Bleſſed are the people that are in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord:</hi> which hath two parts, as ye ſee, like
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:22565:49"/>the portion of <hi>Acſah</hi> that <hi>Caleb</hi> gave her, the Springs above and the Springs beneath; like the <hi>bleſſing</hi> of <hi>Iſaak</hi> divided among his two ſons: the <hi>bleſſing</hi> of <hi>Eſau, the fatnes of the earth and the dew of heaven ſhall be thy portion;</hi> and <hi>the bleſſing of Jacob, the dew of heaven and the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the earth:</hi> the bleſſings of the left hand, <hi>Bleſſed are the people that are in ſuch a caſe;</hi> and the bleſſings of the right hand, <hi>yea bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord:</hi> I muſt ſpeake ſomething of either; and principally, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable to any man ſingle; yet ſo, that I will ſprinkle ſomething as they concerne a nation or people, for which the letter of the text is moſt direct.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> The firſt point is this, <hi>that outward proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and peace is a bleſſing of God, and confers to our happines,</hi> whether you conſider one perſon or an whole people: you muſt underſtand this according to the ordinary diſtinction in this caſe, of <hi>per ſe &amp; per accidens;</hi> it is ſo <hi>per ſe,</hi> in his owne nature, though we through our ſin may <hi>interpolare naturam,</hi> that I may uſe <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians</hi> phraſe of the Divell, in a ſenſe not much different, we may alternature and make that which is of it ſelfe helpfull unto us, hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and thus that truth is evident and cleare.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, becauſe thoſe outward things have an <hi>aptitude in them</hi> to ſatisfie mans naturall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite: for in every man (being a compound nature, the <hi>vinculum</hi> of heaven and earth in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:22565:50"/>which both are, as it were, married by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of his ſoule and body) there is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, inward and outward: now this <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo externus,</hi> agrees with that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as well as his inward with the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the <hi>Platonicks</hi> ſpeake: and therefore ſtands in need of outward things both for neceſſity to ſuſtaine and preſerve him, as alſo for lawfull delight to cheere and refreſh him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, outward good things are to him both the <hi>ſubject</hi> and <hi>inſtruments of many vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> and ſo great advantages in his courſe of godlineſſe, both to furniſh himſelfe, and to helpe and further his brethren, and in both to promote the honor of God in his true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and therefore <hi>David,</hi> who was a man of war, <hi>could not build the houſe of God,</hi> and that <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſon might, <hi>God gave him reſt round about from all his enemies,</hi> and riches in ſuch aboundance that gold in his time was like ſtones in the ſtreet, and ſilver like the duſt of the earth, and hence it is,</p>
               <p>Thirdly that God is ſaid to give theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to his children as <hi>teſtimonies</hi> of his <hi>love</hi> and favor, and as <hi>rewards</hi> of their faithfull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: he brought the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> the <hi>land</hi> of bondage into <hi>Canaan</hi> the land of <hi>promiſe,</hi> out of the land where they were fed with onions and garlick, into the land that flowed with milk and hony: and wiſhes pathetically in the 81. Pſalme, <hi>O that my
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:22565:50"/>people had harkened unto me, and Iſrael had walked in my wayes, I ſhould ſoone have ſubdued their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes, and turned my hand againſt their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries; He ſhould have fed them alſo with the fineſt of the wheat, and with hony out of the rocke, I ſhould have ſatisfied them:</hi> But why do I go about to prove this ſince all the world almoſt is more prone to dote upon theſe externall bleſſings, as the only happineſſe, rather then to doubt, whether they confer to it at all or no! it was well ſaid that he that cal'd Riches <hi>bona</hi> goods firſt, was a better husband then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, but it may be thought that the moſt are ſuch husbands that enquire <hi>who will ſhew us any goods,</hi> as though they were the onely good: and therefore I had more need to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it by making uſe, then prove it by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and a threefold uſe, offers it ſelfe to our conſideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Application. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, <hi>not to faſten our eyes</hi> upon the things themſelves, but to <hi>looke up to heaven and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God the author of all the good we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy,</hi> with humble thankefulneſſe, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full humility: <hi>Thou crowneſt the yeere with thy goodnes ô Lord and thy ſteps drop fatnes,</hi> 65. <hi>Thou prepareſt a table before me in the preſence of my enemyes. Thou anointeſt my head with oyle my cup runneth over:</hi> the Lord hath given us that health and proſperity, and peace and plenty of all things that we injoy, <hi>Bleſſed bee the name of the Lord:</hi> But this not enough but therefore.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:22565:51"/>
               <p n="2">2. Let us labor to <hi>imploy and improve all theſe bleſſings,</hi> that he hath ſo liberally beſtowed on us, to the beſt advantage of his glory: leaſt God complain of us, as of the Jewes once in the Prophet, <hi>That we abuſe his corn, and his wine, and his oyle,</hi> I may ſay, his time and his wit, and his learning, to our unlawfull luſts and lovers: O that now when God hath given us peace from our enemies round about us, while we have meanes, we had alſo minds to build the Temple of the Lord, to advance the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> let us make theſe externall favors, but looking glaſſes through which we may behold the beauty of God that gave them; but as ladders <hi>Scala crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turarum,</hi> and ſtairs to climbe up to heaven: though they have a naturall goodnes in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet they have no morall to us, but in <hi>ordine</hi> to this end without which they are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if theſe be good bleſſings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to happineſſe, then let us ſympathize <hi>with the Saints that want them; Let us pray for the peace of Jeruſalem: Peace be within thy wals, and proſperity with in thy pallaces:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I come to the ſecond and more principall point, which I thought to have ſtood moſt upon, but the time hath prevented me: and therefore I will delineate onely the particulars, and perfect them at ſome other oportunity; for the former is not enough:
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:22565:51"/>he is not an happy man, whoſe bones are full of marrow, and his eyes ſtand out with fatneſſe: that ſwims in pleaſure and riches, and ſhines in purple and ſcarlet and fares deliciouſly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day: that lives in a land that flowes with milke and hony, and waſhes his paths in but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but who then? <hi>Bleſſed is the man, the people whoſe God is the Lord:</hi> the point then is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Our chief happines conſiſts in our union, with God and fruition of him:</hi> the phraſe I think whoſe; God is the Lord imports thus much, they who are in covenant with God, when God accepts ſome for his people and ſervants and teſtifies ſo much eſpecially by acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with his ordinances, and when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally they acknowledge and imbrace him for their God walking in humble obedience to his commandements, ſo that happines ſtands.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in that <hi>relation between us and God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, is maintained by thoſe <hi>actions mutuall</hi> on either part: and thus the truth may be cleare for theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, becauſe <hi>God is the moſt eminent good of all,</hi> imcomparably beyond all other, both ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally and joyntly; and therefore the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him is eſſentiall happines though others be wanting, becauſe there will be more good then evill in ſuch an eſtate, as that man is rich that hath a pearle ſuppoſe of infinite value, worth many thouſands though he want many things.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:22565:52"/>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe God <hi>conteines all other things virtually in himſelfe,</hi> ſo that he that hath God hath all, for he alone can and will give all.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe <hi>God alone can ſupply the want of all the reſt,</hi> in the proper effect of <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe</hi> by himſelfe, and all that we would deſire to find in them, we may have in him; for a full content and quiet of the mind and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the whole appetite, is that which we hunt for, and would faine diſtill, and milk out all the particulars we deſire, but this is richly and royally afforded us by God alone: <hi>How excellent is thy loving kindnes ô God when the children of men put their truſt under the ſhadow of thy wing, they ſhall be aboundantly ſatisfied with the fatnes of thy houſe; and thou ſhalt make them drink of the river of thy pleaſure; for with thee is the fountaine of life, in thy light ſhal we ſee light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The uſes of this point may be theſe,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Application. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, for confutation of all thoſe fond, and vaine opinions of the vulgar, or of the learned Philoſophers about happineſſe, ſome placing it in <hi>pleaſure,</hi> ſome in <hi>honor,</hi> ſome in <hi>riches,</hi> the moſt reaſonable in <hi>virtue,</hi> which well inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted hath ſome truth, we have better learned to place it in the fruition of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for <hi>reprehenſion</hi> of the practiſe of <hi>carnall and worldly men,</hi> that even in the boſom of the Church and Schoole of Chriſt, are ſuch <hi>non proficients,</hi> that they ſeek no further, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the communion with God, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:22565:52"/>thoſe things with great greedineſſe, <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam haec ſint noſtri medicina doloris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, for inſtruction of all, <hi>Many ſay who will ſhew us any good:</hi> but come hither, and as God ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Oſtendam tibi omne bonum,</hi> when he gave him but a glimps of himſelf, &amp; his glory, god is al good god is perfect happines.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For <hi>Exhortation,</hi> there is no man but deſires happines: when the jugler undertook to tell every man what he wiſhed for, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and much company was met to ſee the iſſue of his promiſe with great expectation, out comes the mountebank and bids them be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive, and then ſaid, <hi>Hoc omnes vultis, vili e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere &amp; caro vendere:</hi> and another ſaid <hi>Omnes laudari ſe exoptant,</hi> this <hi>Auſtin</hi> finds fault withall. <hi>At ſi dixiſſent inquit omnes beati eſſe vultis, miſeri eſſe non vultis, dixiſſent aeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nullus in ſua no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agnoſceret voluntate:</hi> Behold then this happineſſe to enjoy the favor of God to have communion with him, labor therfore for this, uſe al means that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, particularly this <hi>Sacrament</hi> to w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God invites us now at this time; wherein God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers himſelfe to every beleever in a moſt neer communion: the <hi>Sybarites,</hi> when they invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a feaſt were wont to give their women a yeeres warning to deck and trim and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelves: this is an anniverſary ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with ſome, and it were to be wiſhed it were not ſo ſeldome with us: let us prepare
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:22565:53"/>our ſelves accordingly to be fit gueſts, for this table, not without the wedding garment: that we may preſent our ſelves before our God adorned with lively faith in Chriſt, and a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute purpoſe of denying our ſelves and our luſts and yeelding ſincere obedience to all his Commandements, and ſo he may dwell with us, and we may walk with him: we may be incorporated into him, he may live in us, &amp; we in him: we may be aſſimilated to him in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſnes and conformed to his image, which neere union is livly ſet forth in this Sacrament, in a word we may be ſo nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with this heavenly mannah that we may go on from ſtrength to ſtrength till we ſee God in Syon:</p>
               <p>Fifthly and laſtly, for Conſolation for thoſe that injoy God a mid all other wants: Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently the Prophet <hi>Habakuck, Although the figtree ſhall not bloſſom, neither ſhall fruit be in the vines: the labor of the Olive ſhall faile, and the fields ſhall yeeld no meat, the fleſh ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there ſhall be no heard in the ſtalls: though all earthly comforts forſake us, yet I will rejoyce in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemb. 26 1639.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Imprimat.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wykes.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:22565:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
